<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Gallant memoirs, or, The adventures of a person of quality written in French by Monsieur S. Bremond ; and translated into English by P. Belon.</title>
            <title>Memoires galans. English</title>
            <author>Brémond, Gabriel de.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1681</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 138 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 69 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A29293</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing B4347</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R30244</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">11273191</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 11273191</idno>
            <idno type="VID">47240</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A29293)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 47240)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1456:10)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Gallant memoirs, or, The adventures of a person of quality written in French by Monsieur S. Bremond ; and translated into English by P. Belon.</title>
                  <title>Memoires galans. English</title>
                  <author>Brémond, Gabriel de.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[10], 124 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for R. Bentley and M. Magnes ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>MDCLXXXI [1681]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>A translation of author's Memoires galans.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Belon, P. --  (Peter)</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-01</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-03</date>
            <label>Claire Tolan</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-03</date>
            <label>Claire Tolan</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:47240:1"/>
            <p>Gallant Memoirs: OR THE <hi>ADVENTURES</hi> OF A Perſon of Quality.</p>
            <p>Written in FRENCH, By Monſieur S. BREMOND.</p>
            <p>And Tranſlated into <hi>ENGLISH,</hi> By P. BELON.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>R. Bentley,</hi> and <hi>M. Magnes</hi> at the <hi>Poſt-Office</hi> in <hi>Ruſſel-ſtreet</hi> in <hi>Covent-Garden,</hi> MDCLXXXI.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:47240:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:47240:2"/>
            <head>To Her Grace the DUTCHESS OF ALBEMARLE</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>MADAM,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>I Am in doubt whether your Grace will have the good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs to Pardon me the Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty that I have taken; but I am perſwaded that a <hi>Cavalier</hi> of the quality that mine is, who croſſes the Seas on purpoſe to have the Honour of entertaining you with a Recital of his Choiceſt Adven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, cannot be ill receiv'd by
<pb facs="tcp:47240:3"/>ſo Generous a Lady as you are. For my part, ſeeing him in ſuch an ardent Paſſion of going to give you that Divertiſement, I could not but abandon him to his hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py deſtiny.</p>
            <q>
               <l>
                  <hi>But if for his Audacious Enterprize,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>He puniſh'd were by thoſe bright Suns your Eys,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>And forc'd to yield his Breath;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Yet where's that Mortal that would not deſpiſe,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>And to Your Greatneſs his Life Sacrifice,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>To gain ſo ſweet a Death?</hi>
               </l>
            </q>
            <p>He is a Stranger, Madam, who is going to chuſe you out in the midſt of one of the greateſt Cities in the World; There might be cauſe for him to fear the committing of a miſtake in this enterpriſe, were there not ſo great a difference between you and all the reſt of your Sex, that thereby you may eaſily be di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinguiſhed
<pb facs="tcp:47240:3"/>from the whole Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſe. Yet at his ſetting forth he has been Furniſhed with moſt faithful <hi>Memoirs</hi> upon your Il<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luſtrious Perſon, as your Grace may here perceive.</p>
            <p>She is a Lady, who by the Qualifications of her mind, as well as thoſe of her Body, ſets a remarkable diſtinction upon her ſelf where-ever ſhe appears; She has the Soul of a Sovereign, Greatneſs and Pomp attend her even in the leaſt of things, no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing in this World, more High, and more Great then her Heart; and at the ſame moment, no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing more ſweet, and more ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerous; inſomuch that accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the varieties of occaſions, with the ſame mind that ſhe is obſerv'd to maintain her Rank
<pb facs="tcp:47240:4"/>with thoſe of her Quality, ſhe is ſeen to ſtoop, for to riſe, and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach to her ſelf; thoſe that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing beneath her greatneſs, fly for ſuccour to her Generoſity. Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gnificent, Liberality, and even Profeſſion it ſelf, are Qualities, which are ordinary with her; Yet not without order, and choice of time, and Perſons. I omit mentioning the Charming air of her Perſon, her agreeable converſation, which affords plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure and delight, in all places that ſhe makes happy with her pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence. Of the agreements of her Face, of her Shape and Stature, and of all that which appertains unto a body perfectly accompli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed; Thoſe are ſuch advantages, as may be term'd in common with other Ladies, who might
<pb facs="tcp:47240:4"/>expect the ſame praiſe for them; but in the repreſentation of a Perſon ſo extraordinary, none but ſuch ſtroaks and touches are to be imploy'd. That ſecret Grace, which is the Spring whence all the others flow, beſtow'd by the Heavens on ſo few Mortals, which all the World admires, but cannot expreſs it, though it is the deſire of all Hearts, does appear in all her words and acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, in ſuch a meaſure, that all that ſhe ſayes or does, is Illuſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted with this particular Charm, which attracts the Love and ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miration of the whole World upon her. None can have a more Penetrating Wit, and quicker apprehenſion then ſhe is Miſtris of, wherewith ſhe unravels in an inſtant the moſt intricate things,
<pb facs="tcp:47240:5"/>and Judges of the moſt Witty ones. It is a very modeſt way of praiſing ſo Illuſtrous a Dut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheſs, to only ſay, that ſhe is a capable Judge of the works of the mind, ſince that it can be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver'd, that when ſhe pleaſes, ſhe can produce moſt accompliſht Pieces of her own growth; And if we will believe thoſe that have a more Particular Knowledge of her ſufficiency; it has happened, that by way of Divertiſement, and as it were in play, her great Genius, hath produced ſuch Works, as the Famous <hi>Drayden</hi> would with Pride have own'd for his. It ſuffices to ſay, that ſhe is the Protectreſs of the curi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Wits, not to doubt that ſhe has a large ſtore of her own. It were very eaſy to know her
<pb facs="tcp:47240:5"/>by ſo many advantageous Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lities, which are ſo rare in this Age; But that which is to make up the perfect knowledge of her, and which is a moſt Glorious and Splendid advantage in a Perſon whom Heaven and Nature have taken delight to accompliſh, is, that ſhe is Daughter unto the Duke of <hi>Newcaſtle,</hi> Grand-Daughter unto <hi>William Duke of Newcaſtle,</hi> who did command the late Kings Armies with ſo much Valour and Conduct, that thereby he has merited that glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious memory which the Hiſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rians mention of him. It is that, that ſhe is Wife unto the Illuſtrious Duke of <hi>Albemarle,</hi> who through his rare merit, has acquired the eſteem and affect <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> of his King, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> has Honour<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> him vvith the Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity
<pb facs="tcp:47240:6"/>of <hi>Knight of the moſt Honour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able Order of the Garter, of one of his Bed-Chamber-Men, one of his Privy Councellors, and Captain of his Guards;</hi> Thoſe Favours from the hands of a Prince, who can diſcern Perſons, were ſufficient of themſelves to make up the Elogy of ſo worthy an Husband, if there was not to be added, that he is Son to that <hi>Great General Monk,</hi> unto whom the Royal Family would be more indebted then it were able to return, if a Subject did not owe all unto his King. What Nobler union then that of thoſe two Houſes, which have been as the two Colombs that have ſupported the Crown, which the moſt furious of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellions had ſo much ſhaken'd, and in whoſe Boſom, the almoſt
<pb facs="tcp:47240:6"/>expiring fidelity of a whole Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, has not only found a refuge, but ſuch a ſuccour alſo, as it ſtood in need of, wherewith to re-eſtabliſh it ſelf.</p>
            <p>Doubtleſs, Madam, but that it is very ſurpriſing, that <hi>I</hi> ſhould at this diſtance, draw ſo juſt and ſo particular a Portraict, that it ſeems as made after the life; but <hi>I</hi> will confeſs to your Grace, that <hi>I</hi> am Indebted for the principal ſtrokes thereof, unto the Illuſtri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Author of <hi>Cleopatra,</hi> and the thing is not ſo extraordinary, that he who has Painted with ſuch neat Touches a Princeſs, for whom he could have no other Paſſion then that, which ſuch Learned men as he himſelf have for Antiquity, ſhould furniſh me with ſuch Curions Colours, in
<pb facs="tcp:47240:7"/>favour of an incomparable Dut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheſs, for whom he has ſo much veneration; Yet <hi>I</hi> muſt confeſs that they had had quite another effect, had they been laid on with his own Pencel; and had his Courteous aſſiſtance accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panyed me to the end, my re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpects would not be reduced to have no other advantage then that of Diſtance, to aſſure you from more then an Hundred Leagues, that <hi>I</hi> am,</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>MADAM, Your Graces, Moſt Humble and moſt Obedient Servant. S. BREMOND.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:47240:7"/>
            <head>Gallant Memoirs: OR THE Amorous Adventures OF A <hi>Perſon of Quality.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HE Mode of writing ones Own Adven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, is now ſo much in Faſhion, that I Thought I might, (without the leaſt ſcruple) make a Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent of Mine to the Publick. For, through the great Noiſe which they have made in the World, they have been known to ſo many Perſons, that
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:47240:8"/>it would be almoſt impoſſible, but that ſome Authors, (as they are in theſe days very greedy of theſe ſorts of News,) would undertake to publiſh mine. I will free them from that trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble; And though ſome other, more vers'd in the manner of Writing then I am, might perform it with more a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greements, and after a more Polite manner; yet I am very certain that none can relate it with more order, and ſincerity then I ſhall do, which is not the leaſt agreeable, ſeaſoning of theſe ſorts of recitals.</p>
            <p>I was born at <hi>Madrid,</hi> of one of the moſt Illuſtrious Families of that Kingdom, and my Father having no more Children but me, he left me at his Death a ſufficient Eſtate, to appear in that Court, in Figure ſuitable to my Birth. But an inclination of viſiting Foreign Countreys, (which is ſo rare in my Countrey-men,) having ſeas'd on me, in my very youth, without the liberty of enjoying that ſatisfacti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on during my Fathers life, I did no
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:47240:8"/>ſooner find my ſelf Maſter of my own liberty, but that I deſign'd to leave the Court of <hi>Spain</hi> for ſome years. I was then in my twenty third year, my af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fairs were in very good order; and I having communicated my deſigns, to ſome of my principal Relations; I went from <hi>Madrid</hi> with their con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent, to begin my Travels through <hi>Italy.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>There lay at that time two <hi>Gal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leys</hi> at <hi>Barcelonia,</hi> that were bound for <hi>Naples;</hi> I came there with a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderable retinue for a Traveller; and every thing concurring with my de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires, my Voyage was ſo happy, as to bring me to <hi>Naples</hi> in eight days of favourable weather. The Duke of <hi>N.</hi> who govern'd there, in Quality of <hi>Vice-Roy;</hi> and who was advertis'd of my comming, as an Intimate Friend to my Family, was Raviſhed with joy at my Arrival, and did give me the kindeſt reception, that I could ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect from his Generoſity and Friend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip.</p>
            <pb n="4" facs="tcp:47240:9"/>
            <p>I found that Court very delight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful, and filled with divers Perſons of Quality; that the Dukes Gallant and Obliging Nature, did draw thither from all parts of <hi>Italy;</hi> He being the Lord in the World, that moſt affect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed all manner of divertiſements, and the moſt Ingenious Contriver of them.</p>
            <p>My Relations had ſufficiently in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructed me, after what manner I was to conduct my ſelf in that Court; but there is not any thing like the practice, which with ſome natural inclinations of my own, did make me learn more in eight days experience, then could have been told me in eight Months. I found, that as in all other Courts, Love, or if you pleaſe, the Miſtreſſes did Govern; each Courtier being provided with his, after the Dukes ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample; and that the time was ill ſpent there, without ſome amorous engage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; Yet I had no great mind to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gage my ſelf ſo ſoon in any ſuch con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern; Love Frights young Perſons,
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:47240:9"/>who know not yet what it is; And beſides, I have ſuch an eſteem for Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty, that I was fully reſolved not to part with Mine, but as late as I could.</p>
            <p>Many times, by reaſon that in all the Matches of Divertiſment, which were daily repeated, I was the only Perſon that did not as the reſt; I was therefore in a manner oblig'd to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertain the Dutcheſs, and thoſe Ladies of her Retinue, that through diſdain, or their ill Fortune, had no ſhare in thoſe Love <hi>Gallantries.</hi> This at laſt put into my mind, that I ought at leaſt to pretend Love. I was young, a Stranger, Genteel, having a great Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue, and making a great ſhew in Expences, which were ſufficient quali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fications to gain Ladies with, who would no doubt have receiv'd me on the bare account of <hi>Gallantry,</hi> as I deſired to be; Yet being to fix upon one, I would willingly have choſen one, for which none could have blam<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d me, there being in my deſign
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:47240:10"/>more of Ambition then of Love. I did caſt my Eyes on divers, and if I durſt have follow'd my own Inclina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, I had not fail'd of adreſſing my ſelf to the Dukes own Miſtreſs; Who from the very firſt moment that I have ſeen her, did appear to me one of the moſt agreeable Perſons of the whole Court. Yet I was not ſo far gone as to venture to become the Concurrant of ſo conſiderable a Rival. All the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Ladies were equally indifferent to me; and be it that the prevention which I had, for <hi>Signora Thereſia,</hi> (ſo was ſhe nam'd) did leave me but very little inclination for all the reſt, or that my time of Love, was not yet come, I knew not on whom to pitch.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Signora Thereſia,</hi> was a Lady of one of the prime Families of <hi>Naples;</hi> her Father being dead, the Dutcheſs, unto whom ſhe was near ally'd, did deſire to have her with her; This invitation being both Honourable and Advanta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geous for her, ſhe left the Countrey where ſhe liv'd, ſome ten Leagues
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:47240:10"/>from <hi>Naples,</hi> and appear'd at Court, as a riſing Sun. There was at that time but very few empty Hearts at Court, but as there is never want of ſuch Perſons as have a great inclination un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to double dealings; Her Beauty was ſoon aſſaulted by divers ſighing Lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers. The Duke, who was the Man of the World, the moſt apt to receive any impreſſions of Love, and who Lov'd the Dutcheſs but juſt as much as needed, not to hate her; though ſhe was one of the moſt Amiable La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies of <hi>Spain,</hi> did find ſuch Charms in <hi>Thereſia,</hi> as did ſufficiently agree with the deſires of his Heart; It is pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bable that if he could have foreſeen, and imagin'd, that an engagement of this nature, would have gone ſo far as it prov'd at laſt, and that it would have had ſuch dangerous conſequen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, he had been juſt enough to have ſaid ſome reſtraint upon his inclina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions; But as it is uſual, Love did not give him time to make all thoſe re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flections, that we have made uſe
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:47240:11"/>of, and he found himſelf ſurpriz'd unawares.</p>
            <p>The Duke did daily behold <hi>There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſia,</hi> who never ſtirr'd from the Dut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheſs, who lov'd her as her own Siſter. All the kindneſſes and endearments, which he did expreſs for her, did paſs at firſt, but for the pure effects of his uſual <hi>Gallantry;</hi> But the Dutcheſs, who knew beſt her Husbands Weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and who had greater cauſe to obſerve him then any other had, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving taken notice that all his care for <hi>Thereſia</hi> did daily increaſe, was not long finding out the true cauſe there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of. It is very rarely that a Woman deceives her ſelf on that account, they rather alwayes believe a little more then there is in it. She was a pene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trating wit, and of a Jealous Temper, as are generally all the Women of that Countrey. She at leaſt fear'd that this <hi>Gallantry</hi> with the cares and aſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duity which attended it, would ſoon be converted into a paſſion; to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent which ſhe did deſign to uſe all
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:47240:11"/>the cautiouſneſs and other remedies, that a prudent and diſcreet Woman ſhould judge neceſſary. She takes <hi>Thereſia</hi> aſide, ſhe tells her all the <hi>Gallantries,</hi> that the Duke had for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly been engag'd in, ſhe makes her Husbands unſconſtancy, ſuch as had been ſufficient to diſguſt a young Lady leſs nice then <hi>Thereſia,</hi> if it had come from any other Hand then that of a Wife; and paſſing from this general diſcourſe unto a ſecret conference, ſhe told her, that if ſhe had not a great care of her ſelf, the ſame Misfortune would fall unto her, as had happened unto others; that the Dukes deſigns were very diſcernable, and that the whole Court did already look upon her, as on his Miſtreſs. <hi>Thereſia,</hi> who was neither young as to the World, nor a novice in <hi>Gallantry,</hi> did harken unto the Dutcheſs whole diſcourſe with an amazement; in which there was much more of affectation then of truth; She had not been the laſt that had taken notice of the Dukes Amo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:47240:12"/>deſigns. It is always ſuch a Charming thing for a Woman to be folow'd, and ſhe who had ſome con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderable time to ſpend at Court, ſhe could not be ſorry to be belov'd by him that did command in it, that ſhe might have the advantage above all the other Miſtreſſes; Yet ſhe was de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſirous to obſerve ſome meaſure with the Dutcheſs alſo, to whom ſhe was oblig'd; and perceiving the Diſtur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bance which was already in the Dut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheſs's mind on that account, ſhe en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavoured to appeaſe it in telling her that ſhe had not yet preceived any ſigns of it, that ſhe had look'd upon all that the Duke had done for her, as on ſo many obliging Teſtimonies from a Kinſ-man, and that ſhe ſhould per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive by her future conduct, that ſhe had no deſign of giving her the leaſt cauſe of Complaint. And in affect from that day ſhe ſhun'd the Duke, and did ever ill Treat him in the Dutcheſs's preſence; Wayes that ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther provoke then allay a Lovers
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:47240:12"/>Paſſion. So ſuddain a Change in a young Lady, who had a Caracter of a mild diſpoſition, who till then had re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived ſo acceptably all that the Duke had expreſs'd of affection towards her, could not but ſurprize him, and make him to ſeek after the Cauſe of his Change. The Dutcheſs was the firſt that he tax'd in his mind, but unwil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling to make any noiſe about it, till he had Learn'd from <hi>Thereſia</hi> the ill Offices which his Wife had render'd him, he waited, (not without much impatiency and reſtleſſneſs,) till the hour in which the Court was wont to walk in the Garden were come, to ſpeak to her about it; The evening was fair, and that day the Court be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing more numerous then of late, the Duke did hope that with the greater eaſe he might meet with ſome oppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunity in the Croud of having ſome private diſcourſe with <hi>Thereſia.</hi> The Dutcheſs was buiſy, with ſome Ladies in gathering of Flowers; and this young Lady, was at ſome diſtance
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:47240:13"/>from them, which gave the Duke, (who was upon the Watch,) the op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunity to accoſt her. She no ſooner did preceive him, but ſhe feign'd to ſhun him, but it was by withdrawing her ſelf the further from the Company, which the Duke judging to his ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage, he redoubled his pace, and perceiving that ſhe was getting into a cloſe Arbour; he run after her, and with an Air in which he expreſs'd more of Love then of Anger; You uſe me very cruely to day, ſayes he, Madam, If I was not convinc'd that I have not done, and that I am incapable of acting any thing that can diſplea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure you, I ſhould intreat you to tell me in what I have fail'd, to beg your Pardon for it; but as all my thoughts and deſires, tend but to ſhew you what eſteem I have for your Perſon, and that I am well aſſur'd, that when you will be pleas'd to examine me, you will find me, more deſerving your Love, then your hatred, I ſhall only intreat the favour of you, to tell me,
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:47240:13"/>who it is, that ſince this day, has inſpir'd you with thoughts ſo prejudiciable a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt me; <hi>Thereſia</hi> with the haſt that ſhe had made from the Duke was come in Breathleſs, having ſeated her ſelf on a Bench of Turfs, ſhe had let him ſpeak without interuption; but having gathered a little ſtrength, My Lord ſais ſhe, with a Languiſhing air, which her wearineſs did give her, if you have any eſteem for me, make it appear in having no longer that com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaiſance for me as you have had, and intreating me with the ſame indiffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ency that you do all the others Ladies at Court, or rather more; neither Seeing nor Speaking to me but as lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle as you can, I, Madam, interrupted the Duke with ſome emotion, that I ſhould be capable of doing what you ſay; that I ſhould have leſs reſpect for you then I have had, and that I ſhould make no diſtinction betwixt you and the reſt of the Women that are here? Rather condemn me to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounce that reaſon that would oblige
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:47240:14"/>me to render unto a young Lady as amiable as you are; a Thouſand times more ſervices then I doe, and know that all the force that I can impoſe up-my ſelf, is in abſtaining from the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formance thereof. <hi>You have then a deſign, to ruine me, my Lord,</hi> reply'd Thereſia. <hi>I ruine you</hi> Madam, reply'd the Duke again, going back a ſtep or two, <hi>Do you know me well?</hi> Added he, Looking on her with Eyes full of paſſion, <hi>and can it be poſſible that ſince the time that my Eyes ſpeak to you, you ſhould have div'd ſo little into my Heart? No</hi> continu'd he Sighing, <hi>you are too clear ſighted; and ſince that it is no longer time for me to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſe any thing from you, Learn that my diſcretion has oblig'd me to conceal till now, which is, that all that can be felt of tenderneſs and vehement deſires in a Soul, I feel from you. How ill you ſerve me in this, My Lord,</hi> interrupted Thereſia, <hi>and how dear will that ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derneſs and vehemency coſt me, I fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſee it too well, and you need but to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:47240:14"/>obſtinatly in it, to render me the moſt miſerable Perſon in the World.</hi> In ending theſe Words, her Eyes became moiſt, which made her to convey her Handkerchief to them to conceal ſome Tears; at which the Duke was ſo ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſibly touch'd, that being wholly tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſported with Love, he ſaid; <hi>What, has ſuch a Paſſion as mine is ſo, full of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpects, of ſo dangerous a Nature in it, that you need to fear it ſo much? You know it,</hi> anſwer'd <hi>Thereſia,</hi> and if you doubt of it continu'd ſhe riſing, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe that ſhe did ſee the Dutcheſs comming with the reſt of her com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany, you will ſoon be further in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form'd thereof. In this manner ſhe went out o the Arbour to meet the Dutcheſs who was ſtrangely ſurpris'd, and did wonderfully change colour, to find her alone with the Duke. <hi>I know not,</hi> ſaid <hi>Thereſia</hi> to her, ſmiling, who per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiv'd what effect this ſight had made on the Dutcheſs her mind, what you may think to find us together, it ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming as if there had been ſomething of
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:47240:15"/>deſign in it, and that we had ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing to ſay in private one to the other; <hi>as for me, I know not well,</hi> (anſwers the Dutcheſs, with a diſdainfull Look,) <hi>what I ought to think of it; but you ſhall ask the reſt of the Company, what Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment they make upon it.</hi> The Duke, who was touch'd to the quick with his Wives words; Seeing <hi>Thereſia</hi> ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing at a ſtand, did anſwer for her, and looking on the Dutcheſs with Eyes full of indignation, <hi>the Company,</hi> (anſwerd he,) <hi>will not have ſo ill an o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinion of me as you have; and for having found me alone with a Lady, it will not give it any ill conſtruction;</hi> and preſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly taking the Dutcheſs by the Hand, to prevent the continuation of that diſcourſe, he walk'd with her; but it was ſaying all that his Amorous reſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, could inſpire him to utter of moſt ſevere againſt her. The Walk was not long, and through this little noiſe, thoſe ſuſpicions which part of the Court had of the Dukes inclinati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons for <hi>Thereſia,</hi> having been wholly
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:47240:15"/>confirm'd therein, thoſe that have ſome Amorous deſigns upon her, and that were not willing to diſpleaſe the Duke, did think of withdrawing them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves towards their former Amours, or to ſeek out for new ones.</p>
            <p>After that, the Duke, in his paſſion had breathed forth all the rage which Love had ſuggeſted to him that night againſt the Dutcheſs, he having had leaſure to make ſome Reflections up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on it, did perceive that in that he had not acted like a true Politician, and that he was not in the right way with his Wife, as thus to Imitate her the more againſt his Miſtreſs. He was de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſirous to repair his fault, and know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing how to flatter the Dutcheſs, the next Morning, at his riſing, there was not any ſubmiſſion that he did not make to her, in asking her Pardon for all his Paſſionate expreſſions; after which he gave her an account of his accidential meeting with <hi>Thereſia</hi> in the Arbour, Proteſting that he had no ill deſign upon her; but that, as ſhe knew
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:47240:16"/>very well, ſeeing that ſhe could not Live without ſome Diverſion, and that if it was not with her it would be with another, he did therefore intreat her (that ſhe might be the leſs troubled at it,) to give way for him to amuſe himſelf with a young Lady of his Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation, (on whom ſhe ſhould daily caſt her Eyes,) then with another, whoſe actions ſhe would not have ſo much opportunity to obſerve, and of whom ſhe might be apt to imagine, more then there would be. <hi>And I do Conjure you,</hi> Anſwer'd the Dutcheſs, <hi>by all that you owe unto a Wife; who ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver had any thoughts in all her life, then of pleaſing you, that you would caſt your Eyes on any other then my Kinſ-woman, to whom I could leſs Pardon ſo unworthy an Action, then to any Perſon elſe. Do all that you pleaſe againſt me,</hi> added ſhe, <hi>I ſhall endure it with patience, but grant me the Favour, not to Diſcourſe my Kinſ-woman; or at leaſt permit her to retire, I conjure you to do it; and if that is not ſufficient,</hi> continu'd ſhe with
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:47240:16"/>Tears in her Eyes, <hi>I beg it of you on my Knees.</hi> The Duke being mov'd at this his Wifes Action and Tears, he took her up, and aſſur'd her, <hi>that he would do all that ſhe ſhould deſire: but that he fear'd ſhe would be the firſt that would repent it; and that in order to cure him from that ſmall inclination, he ſhould be oblig'd to make new Amours in ſome other place, which in time might draw to greater conſequences, for which ſhe ſhould thank none but her ſelf.</hi> The Dutcheſs having agreed to all that, rather then to ſee him in Love with <hi>Thereſia;</hi> the Duke went out of his Chamber as if he had no more thoughts of it: and having left his Wife to her Toilet, he immediatly went to the fair <hi>Thereſia's</hi> Chamber, to put in ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ecution thoſe fair promiſes which he had newly made to the Dutcheſs; Where he found her lain upon her Bed, overwhelm'd in Tears, having paſſed the whole Night in deſperate thoughts, on the adventure which had happened unto her the night before
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:47240:17"/>in the Garden; The Duke overcomed with Sorrow, to ſee her in that con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition; ſhe not having ſo much as pull'd off her Cloaths that night, he caſt himſelf at her feet, and taking hold of one of her Fair Hands, which he brought to his Eyes, to let her feel that he did accompany her Tears with his, he did conjure her to tell him what ſhe ail'd, thus to afflict her ſelf; and making uſe of that little time which he had, he did tell her the moſt paſſionate things, that Love could ſuggeſt unto the tendereſt and moſt tranſported of Lovers. <hi>Thereſia,</hi> who was yet more fearful then he, leaſt the Dutcheſs ſhould ſurpriſe them, did intreat him to Retire; telling him, that ſhe had ſuch tremblings on her, that ſhe could not feel her ſelf, putting off to ſome other time, the clearing of that which he deſired to know from her; to which the Duke did readily obey; after he had demanded the permition of Wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, ſince that he was not to ſee her, as his Paſſion did incline him to do.
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:47240:17"/>He did endeavour, (during ſome days) to conſtrain himſelf before the Dut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheſs, and did feigne the re-ingaging of himſelf in Amours with a certain Lady of whom the Dutcheſs had formerly been extreamly Jealous, putting him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf to a greater expence of <hi>Gallantry</hi> then ever, for her ſake; but all the world did gueſs that this was but a pretence, and that thoſe Feſtivals were celebrated but in Honour to <hi>Thereſia,</hi> who in earneſt did not very well re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh the pleaſure of it, ſhe being of an humour rather to Love the publick ſhew of <hi>Gallanty,</hi> then to be the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret cauſe of it; and though ſhe might eaſily perceive, that what the Duke acted in it, was all on her account; there were ſome certain moments in which ſhe could have wiſh'd, that his Love had outgone his Craft, and that he might Love her ſo well as not to prove alwayes ſo exact a Politician. This would happen to her, chiefly, in publick occaſions, where her Mock-Rival, who was an high ſpirited Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man,
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:47240:18"/>and perfectly Beauteous, did af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect to triumph in her preſence on all the favours which the Duke beſtow'd on her; Inſomuch that ſome time, <hi>Thereſia,</hi> could not forbear having a Grudge againſt him for it; and this is how ſhe did one day declare her mind in Writing, unto him concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>I muſt conſider,</hi> Sir, <hi>that you are a Perſon to be admired in the Art of Feig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, I could ſcarce have believ'd it, for you not only perſwade thoſe whom you would deceive, but thoſe very Perſons al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo that have a hand in the deceit; I in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treat you to continue, for therein you ſerve me better then I can wiſh; and to tell you the truth, there is danger in truſting too much; unto ſuch Perſons as know too well, as you do, how to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſe themſelves. Fare well.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Duke having been ſurpris'd and as ſtruck with a <hi>Thunder-bolt</hi> at the Reading of this Letter, was a thouſand times on the very point of ſpoiling, all that divers dayes of an
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:47240:18"/>extream violence upon <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> gain'd of advantage on the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> mind, and of Running to <hi>Ther<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="4 letters">
                     <desc>••••</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> Chamber, to Juſtifie himſelf from thoſe reproaches, which that No<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e did contain; But thinking that it might be in Raillery, that ſhe had Writ to him after this manner, be would not hazard any thing, and did put off till night, when there was to be a <hi>Ball</hi> in <hi>Maſquerade,</hi> to find an opportunity of clearing that buſineſs with her. This <hi>Ball</hi> was the more magnificent in that all the Courtiers, Lords, and Ladies had been three dayes in preparing them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to appear at it, in moſt ſumptu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous apparel; the Duke whom Love did animate more then all the reſt, did not only extend his magnificence on his own Perſon, but on five or ſix Gentlemen of his Court alſo, who were much of his Siſe, which he caus'd to be Apparell'd juſt like himſelf, the better to deceive the Dutcheſs, ſo that he might with more liberty entert<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap> the Reuteous <hi>Thereſia;</hi> but all <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="24" facs="tcp:47240:19"/>cautions did avail him nothing; the Dutcheſs who was Mask'd, as were all the reſt of the Court Ladies, did pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently diſcern him from the reſt, and did follow him ſo cloſe, that what e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver he could do, he could never get an opportunity to ſpeak one moment to <hi>Thereſia;</hi> who on her part did not make one ſtep to procure him that ſatisfaction; ſo that to rid himſelf of his Wife, he was forc'd to quit the <hi>Ball,</hi> and ſhift his Cloaths, to try whether that would not ſuceed better. The Dutcheſs (who notwithſtanding all thoſe ſhifts, which her unkind Husband did uſe, (was not abſolutely cur'd of that Jealouſie, which ſhe had had of <hi>Thereſia,</hi> had not ſo croſs'd him, but meerly to prevent his ſpeaking to her; and ſhe had taken good notice of the great deſire which he had to do it, and of all the little ſhifts which he had us'd to that purpoſe; ſo that ſhe did no ſooner ſee him go out of the Room, without knowing with what deſign, but that ſhe intreated <hi>Thereſia,</hi> to paſs
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:47240:19"/>into the Chamber with her, where be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing come, ſhe did ingage her; under the pretence of a Frolick, that ſhe would put upon the Duke, to change Cloaths with her. <hi>Thereſia</hi> did very well foreſee the Conſequence of that buſineſs, but ſhe was that day ſo little pleas'd with the Dukes behaviour, that ſhe was not much concern'd at the putting of the Change upon him.</p>
            <p>The Dutcheſs did preſently dreſs her ſelf in <hi>Thereſias</hi> apparrel; and ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving deſired her to ſtay till her return, and alſo given a private order to all her People, not to let her go forth of the Chamber (in caſe ſhe ſhould at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt it,) ſhe return'd to the Company, where ſhe came juſt a moment before that the Duke was return'd. Theſe two Ladies were of ſo exact a ſtature, that it was almoſt impoſſible to be diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern'd; The Duke was no ſooner re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn'd into the <hi>Hall,</hi> but that he caſt his Eyes every where to find out his Dear <hi>Thereſia;</hi> and did no ſooner ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve that the Dutcheſs was not in the
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:47240:20"/>
               <hi>Ball,</hi> that he did run with an extream joy towards the Falſe <hi>Thereſia;</hi> and accoſting her in a Corner of the <hi>Hall,</hi> where he could not be heard of any one; <hi>How well you requited me,</hi> ſaid he, <hi>for all the pains and troubles that you have made me ſuffer this day; you are not only ſatisfi'd with Writing to me the moſt unkind Letters in the World; but to add to your unkindneſs, while I am ſeeking after you every where, and that you ſee what trouble I have to rid my ſelf of a Jealous Woman, you not ſo much as give me the leaſt oppertunity to ſpeak two Words in private to you; on the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary, as if you were of Intelligence with the Dutcheſs, it ſeemes as if you took de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light in augmenting the troubles which ſhe gives me, and you deſign not to make one ſtep towards me, to leſſen them; But lett's form hence;</hi> continued He, <hi>for I have many other reproaches to make you, and I fear leaſt this Importunate Woman, ſhould come again to trouble us; get into your Chamber, and I will be with you in an inſtant.</hi> Having ſaid
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:47240:20"/>this, he riſes from his Seat, and mixes himſelf with the reſt of the Company, to take off all ſuſpicion. The Dutcheſs, who had a mind to ſee how far this Comical part would go, went to <hi>Thereſia's</hi> Chamber, where ſhe ſate on the Bed; <hi>Courage, Monfieur the Duke,</hi> ſaid ſhe to her ſelf, <hi>I muſt needs confeſs that you are a moſt worthy Husband, and I know very well what you deſerv'd, were I not a greater Fool then you; However I am reſolv'd to ſee the end of it; after which I ſhall endeavour to ſerve you with the ſame ſawce: your Perfidious dealings do not deſerve that you ſhould have ſo vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuous a Wife as I am; and it is but rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable that the Letters of</hi> Mart <hi>ſhould be granted in</hi> Loves Wars, <hi>as well as in all others.</hi> The Dutheſs had not time to entertain her ſelf any longer with the like thought, for the Duke comming in, who preſently Kneeling on the Ground before her, <hi>Which of us two,</hi> ſaid he, <hi>is the moſt guilty, and ought to ask the other forgiveneſs? I, for having performed (not without exceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:47240:21"/>trouble) that which you had comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, and horribly conſtraining my ſelf in</hi> Feigning Love <hi>to another, the better to deceive the Dutcheſs; or you for re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proaching me on that account, and for imputing to me as a Crime, that I omit nothing, even to the moſt difficult of things in the World, to endeavour to pleaſe you? Anſwer this,</hi> continu'd he, <hi>and pluck off your Vizard, I beſeech You, that I may ſee You bluſh at the very thoughts of the malicious Trick which this day You have put upon me.</hi> The pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended <hi>Thereſia</hi> did hearken unto all theſe fine things with that ſatisfaction as may be imagin'd; But the <hi>Duke,</hi> who was not pleas'd with her ſilence, no more then at her continuing maſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked, did preſs very hard to ſay ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing; or at leaſt, if that ſhe was re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolv'd to be ſilent, not to deprive him of the only happineſs which he could have near her, which was, of behol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding her Face; ſaying further, That this good fortune did ſo rarely happen to him, that ſhe ought not to think
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:47240:21"/>much of it at that time. But yet no Anſwer to all this; the <hi>Duke</hi> did con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue his Diſcourſe to her, and told her a thouſand fine things on her ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence, adding, <hi>That there was ſome cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain times in which it was more inconve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nient to remain ſilent then to ſpeak, and that ſhe ſhould not take it ill, if he did construe it to his advantage:</hi> And find<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that all that would not do, <hi>What,</hi> continued he, <hi>ſhall I be a whole Eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning by You without drawing one Word from Your Mouth! Well, I know a way,</hi> added he, <hi>to make You ſpeak, at least to call me Names.</hi> Being now ſtreng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thened with this Reſolution, he ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tured to lay his Hand on her Boſome, but the Fair One gave him a Repulſe, becauſe of ſome difference that was between her Breaſts and the true <hi>The<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſia;</hi> but the <hi>Duke</hi> was not in the leaſt daunted at it, and threatening to proceed further if ſhe continu'd ſilent, he began to take greater Liberty then ever; and perceiving that there was but a very ſlight reſiſtance made, and
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:47240:22"/>that both the <hi>Mask</hi> and the <hi>Silence</hi> did invite him to proceed; he went on, and was uſing the extremity of Violence, when the Maſqued <hi>Fair One,</hi> percei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving it time to act another part, pul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led off her <hi>Maſque,</hi> and ſhewed the <hi>Duke</hi> the Face of his own Wife. Never was there ſuch a change put upon a Man ſo <hi>paſſionate</hi> as he was; his ſurprize was ſuch, as may be imagin'd, but not related. He went out of the <hi>Chamber</hi> more affrighted then if he had ſeen all the Spirits of the other World; and as he paſs'd by ſome <hi>Lords</hi> and <hi>Ladies</hi> that were in the next Chamber, he enquired of them what was become of the Lady <hi>Thereſia: The Lady</hi> Thereſia, replied one of the Ladies, who had ſeen her go into that <hi>Chamber</hi> with him, <hi>Was ſhe not with You?</hi> The <hi>Duke</hi> made no Anſwer, but went on, to <hi>ſeek after</hi> what he <hi>asked for.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>Dutcheſs</hi> having compos'd her ſelf out of thoſe diſorders in which her falſe Husband had left her, ſhe went out of the Chamber, and paſs'd
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:47240:22"/>by the <hi>Company</hi> with much haſte, that here Gate, which was ſomewhat dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferent from <hi>Thereſia</hi>'s, might not diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver her. Theſe Lords and Ladies, who did ſee her come forth, did not know what to think of the <hi>Duke</hi>'s Queſtion; <hi>Is not that</hi> (ſaid they one to another) <hi>the Lady</hi> Thereſia? <hi>What ails the Duke?</hi> In fine, they gave an ill conſtruction to the buſineſs, and every one thought of it as he pleas'd. But the <hi>Dutcheſs</hi> having ſome Fears that the <hi>Duke,</hi> who was very <hi>paſſionate,</hi> might ill treat thoſe that had detained <hi>Thereſia</hi> in her Chamber, did run preſently towards it, to prevent Miſchief, where ſhe met him coming forth leading <hi>Thereſia</hi> by the Hand; ſhe had not the Power to look with Patience upon them, and her paſſion (which had been ſo lately ſtirred up with what had paſſed in <hi>Thereſia</hi>'s Chamber,) breaking forth, there was no injurious Words that ſhe did not ſay, nor no Threatenings which ſhe did not uſe, againſt that <hi>Lady:</hi> But ſhe who did think to have
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:47240:23"/>at leaſt as much cauſe of <hi>complaint againſt her,</hi> for the violent detaining of her in the <hi>Dutcheſs</hi>'s Chamber, not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding all her endeavours to get out, did return the <hi>Dutcheſs</hi> as <hi>ſmart Language</hi> as ſhe brought. The <hi>Duke,</hi> who could not remain <hi>Newter</hi> in a buſineſs in which his heart was ſo much concern'd, was twice or thrice upon the point of putting in for one; but at laſt, his Prudence carrying it above the <hi>Tranſports</hi> of his Heart, it not becoming him to take <hi>Thereſia</hi>'s part againſt his Wife, nor agreeing with that tenderneſs of his Heart to take his Wives part againſt his Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreſs, he intreated the laſt to purſue her way, and he conducted her into her Chamber. This buſineſs having made a great noiſe at Court, it was variouſly diſcours'd off, no Perſon knowing what had paſs'd in <hi>Thereſia</hi>'s Chamber.</p>
            <p>The Duke himſelf, did not relate it juſtly, <hi>to his own Miſtreſs,</hi> for Fear of drawing her anger upon him, <hi>as
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:47240:23"/>Doubtleſs it had done, had ſhe known all.</hi> He only told her, that having miſtaken the Dutcheſs for her, and ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving Conducted her into her Cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, he had preſſed her very much to unmask; but ſhe not anſwering his deſires at firſt, he had ſaid ſo many things to her, that at laſt ſhe had diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covered herſelf. <hi>Thereſia</hi> could not forbear ſmiling at the Cheat, though it was at her Coſt; but deſirous to have ſatisfaction at what rate ſoever, for this late inſulting which ſhe had receiv'd without cauſe; ſhe told the Duke that he was to prepare himſelf to ſee her depart the next Morning, and that ſhe could no longer remain with Honour in the Court, after the manner with which the Dutcheſs did daily Treat her; and that ſhe did very well perceive, that how virtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly ſoever ſhe ſhould behave her ſelf, his Wives Jealouſies would be ever finding fault with her, ſo that it were beſt for the ſatisfaction of all parties that ſhe ſhould retire. The
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:47240:24"/>Duke, who did harken unto her without the leaſt motion; <hi>could you,</hi> ſaid he, to her, <hi>Abandon me unto all that rage would make a Man do? For there would be no deſperate attempt, in which your abſence would not lead me; and I do declare to you, that if you have ſo little conſideration for my Life, you may perform what you threaten to do, but you will no ſooner be out of the Gates of</hi> Naples, <hi>but that you will hear of my Death. Alaſs my Lord,</hi> reply'd The<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſia, <hi>What would you have me do? Shall I be all my Life-time expos'd to be ill Treated in the Eyes of the whole Court? And though you could ingage to the contrary, ſhall it be ſaid that after that the Dutcheſs has diverted her ſelf at my coſt, ſhall run down with all the abuſive Language imaginable a Perſon of my Quality in your preſence? What have I done to deſerve ſo ſevere a uſage at her hands? Or rather,</hi> added ſhe with Tears, <hi>What have I done to you, to make you have ſo little regard for my Reputation, that you will not let me quit
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:47240:24"/>this place, that is ſo fatal to my Life? Oh! Heavens, what did I come here to do?</hi> The Duke who was pierced through the very heart, with her Words and Tears, remain'd ſome time without anſwering, Sighing, and looking upon her, with Eyes which did ſufficiently expreſs how much he was concern'd at all that ſhe had ſaid to him; <hi>No, Madam,</hi> ſaid he to her at laſt, <hi>It ſhall not be ſaid, that that Perſon which I moſt Honour in the World, and that I may ſafely ſay I Love a thouſand times more then my Life, does receive any Injury in my Court on my account, and I not reſent it; give me,</hi> continu'd he, <hi>but twenty four hours time, and all Perſons ſhall know what is due unto you, Ah! my Lord,</hi> reply'd <hi>There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſia,</hi> who fear'd ſome dangerous effects from the Dukes Paſſion, <hi>I do conjure you to make no further noiſe about it, there has been but two much already, and I ſhall fear, that at laſt it will all fall upon me; no Madam,</hi> reply'd the Duke, <hi>you have been offended, without
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:47240:25"/>cauſe, I will have that ſatisfaction given that is due to you, and you ſhall ſee Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons return to you without the leaſt noiſe.</hi> The Duke did continue ſome time longer in diſcourſe with that Faire one, to conclude the diverting of her from a deſign to, which, of truth ſhe had no great Inclination; and having left her at laſt, he return'd not to the Dutcheſs, who ſpent the whole night in a fruitleſs expectation of him, the Diſconſolate Lady, did believe, that ſhe had had ſufficient cauſe of Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaint, and of afflicting her ſelf, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the addition of this laſt unkind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, of not ſeeing the Duke all that night, ſhe was extreamly concern'd at it; ſhe ſent ſecretly ſome Perſon of truſt, to learn where he had laine, but none could give her any account of it; at laſt ſhe was inform'd that he had been ever ſince five in the Morning, in <hi>Caſtle Novo,</hi> which was formerly the habitation of the King of <hi>Naples,</hi> and that ſtands at the end of the Palace Garden, belonging to the preſent <hi>Vice-Royes;</hi>
               <pb n="37" facs="tcp:47240:25"/>where he was cauſing an ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>partment to be Furniſhed, with all the richeſt things that were in the <hi>Palace;</hi> this did perplex the <hi>Dutcheſs</hi> more then all the reſt; ſhe knew not whether it was for himſelf, that the <hi>Duke</hi> caus'd this Appartment to be fitted, in order to be ſeperated from her, and to live by himſelf; Or whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther it were for her Rival.</p>
            <p>Either of them was very cruel to her, but much more if it were for <hi>Thereſia;</hi> Judging well that it would be there, that for the future the Court would be kept; and that ſhe ſhould be no longer Confined, but as a uſeleſs Perſon.</p>
            <p>Amongſt thoſe cruel vexations which thoſe ſorrowful thoughts did give her; ſhe had not the patience to let her ſelf be Dreſſed, but juſt as ſhe was in her Night Attire; She goes into her Chair, and is Carried to <hi>Caſtle Novo,</hi> where ſhe really found the <hi>Duke,</hi> who was very buſy to get it Adorn'd according to his fancy;
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:47240:26"/>and who did not give her, as it may eaſily be imagined, an over-kind re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ception.</p>
            <p>The poor <hi>Dutcheſs</hi> was ſo troubled, that beſides the diſorder that ſhe was in, with having paſſed the whole Night without Sleep; ſo many vexa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions which gnaw'd her, did render her ſo unlike her ſelf, that ſhe would have moved compaſſion in any one but her Husband; who did not daign ſo much as once to look upon her; <hi>May a Perſon ask you, My Lord</hi> ſaid ſhe, <hi>with an Humble and Languiſhing voice, for whom is all this? You ſhall ſee it, Madam,</hi> he anſwered coldly, <hi>when it is ready; But however,</hi> reply'd the <hi>Dutcheſs, ſince that I am to ſee it, give me the ſatisfaction as to let me know it before hand, for I muſt confeſs to you, that it is a great trouble to me, and that I am come hither on purpoſe to ask it of you.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Well, Madam,</hi> reply'd the <hi>Duke,</hi> with ſome haſte, <hi>ſince that you ſo much deſire to know it, it is for the</hi> Lady
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:47240:26"/>Thereſia; <hi>For the</hi> Lady <hi>Thereſia,</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plyed the <hi>Dutcheſs</hi> with a trembling voice, which failing her, ſhe Fainted away, falling in a ſwoun, into the Arms of one of the <hi>Dukes</hi> Gentlemen, who was luckily there to ſupport her; The <hi>Duke</hi> who was not ſo hard hearted as to look upon her in that condition, Withdrew himſelf; and the <hi>Dutcheſs</hi> in a little time after com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to her ſelf, inquired where he was? and learning that he was Walking a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone in the <hi>Garden,</hi> ſhe went thither, and threw her ſelf at his Feet; ſhe in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treated him to do what he pleas'd with her, but that he ſhould not give that appartment to the <hi>Lady Thereſia,</hi> but that ſhe ſhould remain with her, where he ſhould ſee her if he pleas'd from Morning till Night.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Duke</hi> raiſing her up with ſome Signs, that he was mollified with her ſubmiſſion, did tell her that he had given his word to his Kinſwoman, that he could not fall from it, and that the thing was to be mention'd to her
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:47240:27"/>ſelf; and endeavours made to bring her to live with her again.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Dutcheſs</hi> did perceive to what all that tended, and to what cruelty ſhe was expoſed thus to be obliged to ſubmit to a Rival; But there was nothing that ſhe would not have done to prevent her being lodg'd in that re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tired place, which ſhe looked upon as on the greateſt and laſt of all her trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles; So that having left the <hi>Duke,</hi> ſhe Retired to her own Appartment; whence ſhe ſent one of her Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men to <hi>Thereſia,</hi> intreating her to be willing to live with her again, as ſhe had formerly done, and to forget all that was paſs'd.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thereſia,</hi> received this <hi>Embacy</hi> with a great Coldneſs, and made an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer unto the <hi>Dutcheſs</hi>'s Compliment, <hi>That ſhe thank'd her for the Honour that ſhe did her; but that having Reſolv'd to withdraw her ſelf from the Court, that ſhe might not give her any further occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of diſquiet, ſhe did intreat her to diſpenſe with her from it.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="41" facs="tcp:47240:27"/>
            <p>The <hi>Dutcheſs</hi> did well perceive that ſhe muſt reſolve her ſelf, to make all the advances; and that nothing would be done, except ſhe went her ſelf in Perſon, to intreat her to it; Theſe are ſtrange kind of Submiſſions, and that coſt very dear, on ſuch occaſions, to a Woman of that Quality, Young, and Beuteous as ſhe was, in reſpect of a Rival, who was her Kinſwoman, and who ſhe had her ſelf invited to Court, to be as it appear'd, her Sorrow and Ruine.</p>
            <p>Nothing more ſevere in this Life, yet there was no way to avoid it, if ſhe would prevent the deſign of <hi>Caſtle Novo,</hi> which would cauſe her a thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand times more troubles then that; therefore ſhe went thither, and it is certain, that this Interview, was one of the rareſt Scenes, as ever was Acted; <hi>Thereſia,</hi> although her heart was yet griev'd at the injury which ſhe receiv'd the Night before, Could not deny a Reconciliation with the <hi>Dutcheſs;</hi> after ſo many Civilities it was, who
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:47240:28"/>ſhould outdoe one another in Cour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſies, and one would have Sworn that they had both forgot their rancour, and all the reaſon which they both had, not to forget one another, ſo much power has certain Conjunctures of time on the minds of Women; in whom it is ſaid, that Paſſions are very Powerful.</p>
            <p>There was then made a kind of Reconciliation, at leaſt in appearance, for as to the Inward, there was pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paring a greater War than ever; The Duke was the Perſon that was the moſt pleas'd at it, who over-joy'd for having compas'd his ends, was deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous to Publiſh the ſhare that he took in this new Friendſhip, by living in ſo good an Intelligence with the <hi>Dut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheſs,</hi> that there was no care or regard that he had not for her, as if he ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver had any other deſire in his mind then to pleaſe her.</p>
            <p>Things were much at this rate, when I came to this Court; Whenever I look'd on <hi>Thereſia,</hi> ſo Beauteous and
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:47240:28"/>Charming as ſhe was, I did in ſome meaſure excuſe the <hi>Duke</hi> for being taken with her; for of truth, there was nothing more Amiable; But when I did turn my Eyes upon the <hi>Dutcheſs,</hi> who was alſo a Beautiful young Lady, that had no other fault in her, (as to the <hi>Duke,)</hi> but that of being his Wife; I had a great com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſion for her; and it wanted but lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle, that I did not offer my ſelf to repair that defect; and as if it was my fault, to be concern'd in all the <hi>Dukes</hi> Amours, whom I was oblig'd to reſpect for a Thouſand reaſons; it daily fell to my lot to entertain her; of which Imploy I did acquit my ſelf with ſo much compliſance, that it might eaſily be perceived it was not very troubleſom to me, and of truth, as the <hi>Dutcheſs</hi> had a world of Wit, and that I had no particular de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigns on any Perſon except <hi>Thereſia;</hi> I would have always preferred her to all others, if it had been in my own choice, but as I was not to pretend
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:47240:29"/>any thing on that ſide, no more then on the other, and that I was ſeeking after ſome ſubject that might give me ſome occaſions of expences, and of appearing rather then to be tyed unto, by any other inclination; I was oblig'd to turn my Eyes another way, to find out one that might be worth my Labour.</p>
            <p>The day of the <hi>Dukes</hi> Feſtival was growing near; and as on that day the Court was to be more Gallant then e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver, and the Ladies better Adorned then all the reſt of the year, I did reſolve to ſtay until that day; and in the mean time to continue my uſual Devoirs towards the <hi>Dutcheſs,</hi> who did give me ſufficiently to underſtand, that ſhe was well pleas'd with it, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving told me more then once, that I was not altogether uſeleſs in aſſiſting her, to ſupport the Domeſtick vexa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions which ſhe was to ſuffer.</p>
            <p>At laſt, that day came in which I did deſign to be in Love, or at leaſt, in which I was to find out a Miſtris to
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:47240:29"/>make me ſo. There were but few Lords at Court that had ſuch Curious and Rich Apparel as I had; and I did that day put one on, which had not yet been ſeen, and which was as fit to make my ſelf be belov'd, (as ſome times ſome have been by that means,) as any that ever was invented; I was very much look'd upon, and not to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend my ſelf on the particulars of the <hi>Regalio,</hi> which the <hi>Duke</hi> gave, which was one of the moſt magnificent, that ever had been made; I ſhall only ſay as to what concerns my ſelf, that be it, the inclinations which I had already for <hi>Thereſia,</hi> or the tender compaſſions that I did feel from the <hi>Dutcheſs,</hi> who certainly were the <hi>two Perſons of the Court, moſt deſerving to be conſider'd;</hi> I could not ſee any thing amongſt all the reſt, that was of Power to draw ſo much as one ſingle Sigh from me; ſo tha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> I was in great danger to return home, as indifferent as I was to come forth: when that towards the latter part of the <hi>Banquet,</hi> where every one
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:47240:30"/>did ſet a value upon his Inclinations in Drinking of Healths: all the whole Railery being fallen upon me, for Drinking none but ſuch as were ſerious.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Duke</hi> who was the Man in the World, that had moſt Wit, and who did not let ſlip the leaſt occaſion in which he might oblige me, did ſpeak of my indifferency unto the <hi>Ladies;</hi> ſaying, <hi>that it was a great ſcandal to their Beautyes, that I had been ſo long at the Court of</hi> Naples, <hi>as cold and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenſible as the firſt day of my Arrival.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>I do Swear, by the God of Love,</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinu'd he, <hi>That this the day of my Fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtival ſhall not conclude before I ſee an end to this indifferency.</hi> Upon this pulling from off his Finger, a very fair Diamond; <hi>Here my Lord,</hi> ſaid he, <hi>Here is a Ring that I preſent you with, and which I do intreat you to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtow without any diſtinction of Perſons, on that Lady of the Company which you Judge to be the moſt Beautiful.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="47" facs="tcp:47240:30"/>
            <p>The ſport was pleaſant, but I did find ſome conſiderable danger in it; there being no queſtion to be made, but that my preferring of any one be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the reſt, would offend the major part; For Women are never in the humour of yielding any advantages to one another, eſpecially in matters of Beauty: Therefore I did intreat the <hi>Duke</hi> to diſpence me for it; but beſides, I did uſe much ſtronger mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tives which I was unwilling to declare.</p>
            <p>However I was condemn'd to it, by the loud clamour of the whole Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany, who were deſirous to ſee on which ſide my heart would incline.</p>
            <p>This did oblige me to riſe, and to preſent the Ring unto the <hi>Dutcheſs.</hi> This was preſently look'd upon, ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther as an act of prudence, then an effect of my inclination. For though the <hi>Dutcheſs</hi> was in the Eyes of all the World a moſt Beautiful Woman, it was reaſonably thought, that I would not addreſs my ſelf there, or at leaſt declare my ſelf ſo openly be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:47240:31"/>the <hi>Duke</hi> in caſe that my incli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nations ſhould lead me that way; but it was concluded, that I had thought fit to preſent to the Wife that Ring with which the Husband had honour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed me.</p>
            <p>If there was any one, to whom what I had done was diſpleaſing, it was <hi>Thereſia,</hi> who did highly pretend to that advantage.</p>
            <p>As to the <hi>Dutcheſs,</hi> I did render her ſuch a ſignal and ſenſible piece of ſervice, in giving her that Tryum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phant advantage over her Rival before the <hi>Duke,</hi> that ſhe had not thought to expreſs too large an acknowledg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of it, though at that very mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, ſhe had given me her whole heart, in exchange of that Diamond.</p>
            <p>Peradventure, that had I followed my Inclinations, <hi>Thereſia</hi> had had a greater ſhare in them, then the <hi>Dut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheſs;</hi> but I was not ſo bad a Politi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tian, and I foreſeeing the Advanta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geous Judgments that would be given me on that account; and that beſides
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:47240:31"/>it was the beſt way to pleaſe all in this Addreſſing my ſelf to the <hi>Dut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheſs;</hi> I did not defer one moment from making her that preſent, of which I had ſome confidence, that ſhe would keep a good account: Howe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver the <hi>Duke</hi> was pleas'd to have this my choice, to paſs for an exact decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of Love in all its forms; Upon which the <hi>Dutcheſs</hi> was preſently ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luted as my Miſtris.</p>
            <p>I did Drink her health, as being her <hi>Gallant,</hi> and all the reſt of the Night that this <hi>Feasting lasted,</hi> was ſpent in <hi>Gallant Ceremonies,</hi> upon the conqueſt of my indifferency, to the Honour of the <hi>Dutcheſs's</hi> Beauty, <hi>that had over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come the Inſenſibility of my Heart,</hi> and who did appear that night of better humour then ſhe had ever been ſeen before.</p>
            <p>As for <hi>Thereſia,</hi> from that day, ſhe declar'd open Wars againſt me; not that I had any great acceſs or Famili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>arity with her before, <hi>I had ſcarce Spoken three times to her,</hi> and that too,
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:47240:32"/>by accident and very ſuccinctly, but I had always found her very complai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſant with me, either in the general converſations, or in other occaſions, when ſhe did always delight to praiſe me, and to approve of all that I did; but after the buſineſs of the <hi>Diamond,</hi> ſhe was in perpetual debates with me on all accounts, <hi>expreſſing many ſighs,</hi> with a thouſand other Averſions and Antipathies againſt me, <hi>from which I did not draw worſe conſequence, then from all the Complaiſance that ſhe had formerly had for me.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In a word, <hi>we did live like real ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies,</hi> though in the bottom there was nothing which was leſs in our hearts then hatred. Mean time, all thoſe ſeeming contrarieties of humours, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween <hi>Thereſia and my ſelf,</hi> did not a little contribute to Augment certain motions, <hi>which the Dutcheſs did feel of not hating me.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>She was Born with great inclinati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons to virtue; but at laſt the Love which ſhe had for the <hi>Duke</hi> decrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing,
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:47240:32"/>
               <hi>as fast as he did render himſelf unworthy of it.</hi> It did leave an empty place in her Heart, <hi>which ſhe had a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire to fill up with ſome Idea, that might pleaſingly Revenge her, of that wrong which was offer'd to her Beauty.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And I believe, that ſhe already did look upon me as a Perſon that would be very fit for that purpoſe; but were it, that I did put forward ſufficiently, or that the <hi>Dutcheſs,</hi> in which Hon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our ſtill held a combate <hi>Maugré,</hi> the reaſons which ſhe gave herſelf of not following its Dictates on her Husbands account, did not give me a ſufficient overturn to make her an open Decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration; Our Affairs did reſt for ſome time at a ſtand, in which Love can ſcarce be reckon'd any thing, <hi>though it had a being,</hi> till that one day that I went to give the <hi>Dutcheſs</hi> a viſit, one of her <hi>Gentlewomen</hi> in whom ſhe moſt confided, having told me, <hi>that ſhe was walking upon the</hi> Tarraſs, <hi>and that I was come the moſt luckily in the World to comfort her, in a relation which ſhe
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:47240:33"/>had newly received;</hi> I preſently went to her, and having found her with Eyes full of Tears, holding a Paper in her Hand, I inquired of her, with a paſſionate Air, <hi>what cauſe ſhe had to afflict her ſelf ſo ſeverely? Here,</hi> reply'd ſhe, giving me the Paper to Read, which was a Note that the <hi>Duke</hi> had lately Writ to <hi>Thereſia, this Note will ſufficiently inform you of it.</hi> I took it from her, and in it Read as follows.</p>
            <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
               <body>
                  <opener>
                     <salute>Well Madam,</salute>
                  </opener>
                  <p>
                     <hi>SInce that you do deſire one day lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, to examine if I have well de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved that favour which I have been requeſting from you theſe ſix Months, or rather ſix ages, I grant it you, but con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider, that it is the laſt day of my Life, if you defer any longer the happineſs which I expect; I ſhall to morrow give a Feſtival at the</hi> Poggio Reale, <hi>to ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lebrate ſo bleſſed a day, which I ſhall ever account the happineſs of my life.</hi>
                  </p>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <pb n="53" facs="tcp:47240:33"/>
            <p>I ended the Reading of that Note, which I could not return to her, without Smiling; at which ſhe ſaid, <hi>You take but very little ſhare in Peoples afflictions, ſince that you can laugh at him.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Heaven is my Witneſs, Madam,</hi> ſaid I to her with a ſerious look, <hi>that no other Perſon can be ſo much concern'd as I am at yours, and that if my Bloud could repair it, I would offer it to you all to the laſt drop, but—But, there is no occaſion here for Bloud,</hi> Interrupted the <hi>Dutcheſs, only tell me what you think of the</hi> Dukes <hi>carriage? You too well know, Madam,</hi> I anſwered, <hi>what I am to think of it, without obliging me to explicate my ſelf on ſo nice a point.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>No,</hi> reply'd ſhe, <hi>I will have you to immediately tell me, what your thoughts are on this Subject?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>I obey, Madam,</hi> ſaid I, <hi>Since you compel me to it; but if I fail in my reſpects to your concerns, blame none but your ſelf for it.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="54" facs="tcp:47240:34"/>
            <p>
               <hi>I value it not,</hi> reply'd ſhe, <hi>Speak, I will have it ſo; Tell me what one may Judge of ſuch Proceedings as are the</hi> Dukes.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>What ſtrange fancys is there in the World,</hi> ſaid I; <hi>for there is no Perſon that does pretend to the leaſt knowledge in Beauty, Wit, and all other things, that men of Judgment are taken with, that would not prefer you to all that is ſeen of moſt Charming at Court.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Are you well pleaſed,</hi> ſaid ſhe, with a little Redneſs, that came over her Face, <hi>of what you ſay? And may I flatter my ſelf that you Speak ſincerely?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>I ſhould ſay a thouſand times more if I durſt,</hi> I reply'd, with ſome Emotion of Spirit; <hi>Dare it, then,</hi> anſwered ſhe, <hi>And ſay all that you think in my con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerns, I do conjure you to it.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This was giving me ſufficient liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, yet I did ſtagger for ſome time, but at laſt finding my ſelf too far gone to retire, and obſerving that the <hi>Dutcheſs</hi> Eyes, as well as Words did expect a further Explanation.</p>
            <pb n="55" facs="tcp:47240:34"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Well, Madam,</hi> ſaid I, <hi>ſince that you command me to Speak, I will tell you, that for my part, I am ſo concern'd at the</hi> Dukes <hi>unjuſtice, that if you had judg'd me worthy to fill up his place, I had long ſince offered my ſelf to repair thoſe wrongs that he does you: for in a word there is nothing more deſerving then you are.</hi> And finding that ſhe remai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned ſilent.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Yes, Madam,</hi> continu'd I, <hi>If that the vows of a Heart that never yet Lov'd any thing elſe, and that cannot Love any thing but you, does not appear unto you wholly unworthy of that Choice, per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit me to Conſecrate them to you this very moment; The</hi> Duke <hi>is of the Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mour of thoſe, that are never well pleas'd with their own Fortune, be it never ſo good; Another would make better uſe of it; And the least of thoſe Favours which he Condemns, is able to render a Perſon most happy.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A Perſon Madam,</hi> continu'd I, <hi>Born with thoſe Excellent Qualities that you poſſeſs, ſuch as are of Power to Create
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:47240:35"/>Love in the most inſenſible Perſons, ought not to ſuffer thoſe kind of Scorns; I do forget my duty, Madam,</hi> added I, <hi>but your Intereſt is Dearer to me then my Life, and I having at first taken your Intereſt by reaſon meerly; Love now has ſo firmly united me unto it, that I ſuffer the ſame pains you endure; others in your Place, has already taken ſome Reſolution to force People to Reaſon, but thoſe are extremities, which makes too much noiſe, and that are ever avoi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded by Rational Perſons.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>There are milder ways to Reduce a Man to his Duty; after which if he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mains Obstinate, the only way is to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn Scorn for Contempt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>There being nothing in all that I had ſaid to the <hi>Dutcheſs,</hi> in which I was not highly concern'd; I therefore did not omit ſaying any thing which I thought would invite her to believe me.</p>
            <p>I muſt confeſs that then there was yet more of Vanity then of Love in my Deſign; And that ſeeing I could
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:47240:35"/>not be the <hi>Dukes Rivall to his Miſtris,</hi> a thouſand Reaſons of Youth did in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gage me not to looſe the fair oppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunity of becomming the <hi>Dutcheſſes Gallant.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>She was, or at leaſt did appear to me to be concern'd at what I had ſaid, and with Sighs which were mixed with Anger againſt her perfidious Hus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band, and that had ſome mixture of Gratitude towards me; She let me know, that it was not from that day, that ſhe had taken notice of my being concern'd at her Misfortunes, and that the truſt that ſhe had always repos'd on me in all her Afflictions, might have ſufficiently inform'd me, of the eſteem which ſhe had for me, and of the diſpoſition which was in to make uſe of my Councils; Further confeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing, that nothing had ever pleas'd her ſo much, as the preſent which I had made her of the King, which daily did come into her mind with delight, and that of truth ſhe might one day ſhew me how ſenſible ſhe was of it, if the
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:47240:36"/>
               <hi>Duke</hi> ſhould drive her to it. I did in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour to Animate her the more, and at laſt before we parted, to ſhew me that her indignation was not far from breaking forth; ſhe gave me her hand to Kiſs, and let me on the <hi>Terras,</hi> ſaying, <hi>Prepare your ſelf to Morrow, to ſee great things come about.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I did return very well ſatisfied to ſee my Affairs advanced ſo far on that ſide, and the next Night after this converſation, I paſs'd with moſt pleaſing fancies.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Poggio Reale,</hi> is a place of pleaſure, ſome three Miles diſtant from the <hi>City,</hi> where the <hi>Duke</hi> did frequently divert himſelf.</p>
            <p>The Company were very numerous and <hi>Gallant</hi> there that day, and the Supper moſt Magnificent; but that which was moſt pleaſant to behold, and made, on deſign to amuſe the People, were a great number of Fire Works, which laſted above an hour. They had ſcarce been Lighted, that every one running to ſee that pleaſant
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:47240:36"/>ſpectacle; the <hi>Duke and Thereſia</hi> un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der pretence of the ſame curioſity, diſapear'd from the Eyes of the <hi>Dut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheſs,</hi> who had diligently obſerv'd them, till then that ſhe loſt the ſight of them in the Confuſion.</p>
            <p>She was immediatly diſturb'd at it, and ſought after them, and meeting me by accident, <hi>Do you not know</hi> ſaid ſhe, quite out of Breath, <hi>What is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come of the</hi> Duke <hi>and</hi> Thereſia? <hi>No, Madam,</hi> I reply'd ſmiling at the trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble ſhe was in, <hi>And if you would be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve me, you would not ſeek any fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther after them; You will but put by an adventure, which if not atchieved to day, will be ſo to Mo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>row.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>It is no matter,</hi> reply'd ſhe, Bluſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, <hi>I will go ſee if they are not in one of the Arbours of the</hi> Labyrinth, <hi>you will do well to repair there, where, if I find them not, and meet with you, it is likely that I ſhall ſeek them no further;</hi> I promis'd her to go there, and did follow her preſently after.</p>
            <pb n="60" facs="tcp:47240:37"/>
            <p>This <hi>Labyrinth,</hi> is very large, and the Alleys of it ſo cloſe cover'd, that at mid-day there appear'd but a dull Light in them; ſo that I, who did not well know the windings of it, and that fear'd to ingage my ſelf in that obſcurity, ſo far, as not ſo eaſily to get out again; I went a ſlow pace on, till at laſt I did think that I heard a voice; I went forward without any noiſe, to endeavour to underſtand what was ſaid, and at laſt I under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood that it was the <hi>Dutcheſs, Well, My Lord,</hi> was ſhe ſaying, <hi>Will you this Night Revenge me of all the</hi> Dukes <hi>Injuries? He is falſe, and does not de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve the pains that I take after him, I know it, and ſince that he is the only cauſe that I have met with you here a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone, it will be your own fault if I return not well ſatisfi'd, for my fruitleſs ſearch after him ſo far without ſucceſs.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This Diſcourſe did the more ſurpriſe me, by reaſon that I knew it to be intended to me, that the <hi>Dutcheſs</hi> did miſtake her ſelf, and that to both our
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:47240:37"/>Sorrows, it was peradventure the <hi>Duke</hi> that was with her; upon this I did harken more attentively then be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, to hear what he would anſwer; But preſently after I heard the <hi>Dutcheſs</hi> proceed in this manner.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Why are you ſo ſilent? And what is become of that ſenſibility which you have ſhewn till now for all my Troubles? And that has made you ſhare in all my ſorrows and afflictions, as well as in the aver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion which I have againſt a Perfidious Husband? Will you become inſenſible when it is no longer time to be ſo?</hi> This Diſcourſe did make me mad, not ſo much becauſe that I could not anſwer her expectations, as I would have done, if I had been in that place that the <hi>Dutcheſs</hi> did think me to be, as for the evil conſequences that would follow, both as to her, as well as to my ſelf, eſpecially if it was the <hi>Duke</hi> that ſhe ſpoke too, as I had little rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon to doubt it. There being none but he that could keep thus the Lady ſo long in her Ignorance.</p>
            <pb n="62" facs="tcp:47240:38"/>
            <p>He had that day on a <hi>Juſtecoes</hi> im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broider'd as I had, and I did gueſs, that that might be the very occaſion of the miſtake.</p>
            <p>During theſe Tranſactions, I got ſo near the place they were in, that there was only the Hedge between them and us, and I could hear all, even to the <hi>Dutcheſſes</hi> Sighs, who judging ill things from this ſilence, and the indifferency which ſhe found in the Perſon which ſhe took from me, She began to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amine him more nearly; there was a great ſilence, and I fearing to make ſome noiſe, did ſeat my ſelf on the Ground, to ſee the effects of ſo ſad an accident; when I heard ſome body move behind me, who pulling me by the Coat, and caſting his Arms about my Neck, did bring his Mouth cloſe to my Ears, <hi>Is it you My Lord,</hi> ſaid he, as low as he could? <hi>I was affraid that you had met with the</hi> Dutcheſs, <hi>but I believe that it is the Lord</hi> N. <hi>that is with her,</hi> (continu'd he,) naming me:</p>
            <pb n="63" facs="tcp:47240:38"/>
            <p>The ſurpriſal that I was in, joyn'd to the pre-ocupation that I had of what was paſſing with the <hi>Dutcheſs,</hi> had ſo ſtrangely diſturbed my mind, that I did ſcarce know the Perſons voice, but that the conjuncture of the place, the Cloaths that I felt, and what had been ſaid to me, did perſwade me that it was <hi>Thereſia,</hi> who doubtleſs had taken me for the <hi>Duke,</hi> while the <hi>Dutcheſs</hi> did miſtake the <hi>Duke</hi> for me.</p>
            <p>At laſt, the <hi>Dutcheſs</hi> finding the mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtake at the touch of her Husbands Cloaths, ſhe had occaſion to make uſe of all the quickneſs of her Wit, to get off of ſo bad a buſineſs. Therefore in an inſtant recalling into her mind all the cauſes of Anger that ſhe had, to animate her ſelf the more againſt her Husband; <hi>Go, thou Traitor,</hi> ſaid ſhe to him, <hi>go ſeek thy</hi> Thereſia; <hi>for I am too virtuous to carry on this diſguiſe any further, thou well deſerveſt that I ſhould make thee feel all thoſe anguiſhes which my fidelity keeps from thee, but if thou doſt perſist in thus making me grow deſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate,
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:47240:39"/>I will not warrant thee but that I may perform in earnest that Perſonage, which I but now acted.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This ſuddain charge did ſmell too much of Art, not to be perceiv'd by ſo skilful a man as the <hi>Duke,</hi> who re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flecting upon every little circumſtance of this adventure, did amongſt the reſt, find that the embraces with which the <hi>Dutcheſs</hi> had accoſted him at firſt, were too full of heat, and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>companied with too many Ardent Sighs, to proceed from a Woman, who had a heart fill'd with Jealouſies only, and that had no other deſign then to feign; he was not Ignorant of the Affairs of the World, and his own experience had made him too capeable, to be ſubject to make ſo groſs a miſtake, ſo that ſpeaking with the voice of a Perſon that had no mind to be couſen'd by a Womans Subtilty.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>If I miſtake not,</hi> ſaid he, <hi>Madam, there is much more of mistake then of feigning in this buſineſs.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="65" facs="tcp:47240:39"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Confeſs the truth, and that you did not expect me here, that you intended that Honour to ſome other, and that I own to my ſilence, and to my Cloaths per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps, the ſaving of the Shameful Conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of this adventure.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Who could have ſeen the <hi>Dutcheſs</hi>'s Face, might eaſily have gueſt at the tranſactions within her breſt; ſhe was at firſt ſomething daunted at the <hi>Dukes</hi> Words, but at laſt taking Courage, by the advantage of the obſcurity of the place; <hi>Well,</hi> (reply'd ſhe,) <hi>Were it true as you ſay, that this was an appoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and that I had taken you for an other; For whom have you taken me, and what came you to do here?</hi> At this kind of confeſſion, the <hi>Duke</hi> paſſing from doubts to a certainty of the <hi>Dut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheſs</hi>'s miſtake; He did take it very ill, that ſhe made no difference be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween a Wives Treachery, and that of an Husbands, going about to prove to her by good and ſufficient Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, that the firſt did thereby diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>honour a whole Family, and that the
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:47240:40"/>other was meer <hi>Gallantry;</hi> But the <hi>Dutcheſs,</hi> maintaining her Right, would make him ſee that the obligation be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing equal, ſo was the injury alſo; and that if the uſe of Falſe-hood was eſtee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med more pardonable in Men then in Women on that account, it was only becauſe that they as more Impudent, had made it more frequent amongſt them, then it was amongſt Women; But that ſhe thank'd Heaven for't, Women had began ſo to order thoſe Affairs, as to render them equal on both ſides; That ſhe had already tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mented her ſelf ſufficiently on that ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count, but that ſhe would no longer be a Fool, and that ſhe ſhould ſoon find out ſome body, that would com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort her for all his Baſeneſs.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Could we not know,</hi> ſaid the <hi>Duke,</hi> who was not pleas'd with all thoſe rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonings, as may well be imagin'd, <hi>whom you have made choice of, to render you that ſingle piece of ſenſe? You need not trouble your ſelf about it,</hi> anſwer'd ſhe, <hi>Go find out</hi> Thereſia, <hi>who doubtleſs
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:47240:40"/>will be tryed in waiting for you, and leave me here, for I am weary of you.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Nay, this is driving too far,</hi> ſaid the Duke, <hi>It ſuffiſes that you have ſhewed me what you are willing to do, without requiring of me ſuch a Complaiſance, as is not uſually deſired from an Hus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>The whole Complaiſance is for your ſelf,</hi> reply'd the Dutcheſs, <hi>you are expected, and I conſent that you ſhould go, what would you have more; I will</hi> reply'd the Duke, <hi>that whoſoever ſtays ſhould ſtay on ſtill, and I will remain by you; If you have ſo much goodneſs left as to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit; I think it a very humble request,</hi> added he, <hi>and that an Husband like me, is well worth a Gallant.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>I ſhall tell you that,</hi> reply'd the Dut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheſs, <hi>when you will ſhew me that I am well worth a Miſtreſs.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>After theſe Words there was a Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral ſilence reign'd, whence it might eaſily be conjectured, ſome conjugal reconciliation to proceed.</p>
            <pb n="68" facs="tcp:47240:41"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Thereſia,</hi> who had no ſooner heard the <hi>Dukes</hi> voice, but that ſhe did en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour to be gone from me, had I not held her by the Coats, did ſtrive more then ever to get out of my hand, when ſhe perceiv'd to what a conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion the Dialogue was come, which ſhe underſtood as well as I did.</p>
            <p>But there was no intreating of her, ſhe was ſeated on the Graſs as I was, I lay at her Feet, giving her to under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand as well as I could, that we two were the happieſt couple of the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venture; There is no queſtion that how hard ſoever it be, for any one to ſee that which they love in the poſſeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of another, nothing inſpires ſo much Indignation, as when it is in the Husbands.</p>
            <p>Of all <hi>Rivals,</hi> they are the moſt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſufferable, and the contempt that is had for them; does frequently out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſs the hatred that one would have againſt others.</p>
            <p>For my part, if any thing was cape<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able of Diverting me, during the vex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ation
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:47240:41"/>that I was in, becauſe another held my place; It was the ſatisfaction which I had to imagine that <hi>Thereſia</hi> had as great a ſhare in it as I had; for thoſe kind of things have a far grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter effect upon Womens minds, then Mens.</p>
            <p>Mean time, as in all ſuch Fair op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunities there is ſome putting for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards, I did then endeavour, (not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding the Hatered that there was between that fair one and me;) to make uſe of this conjuncture in taking ſome ſmall liberty.</p>
            <p>The Darkneſs of the place, its Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuation, the example of others, all did ſeem to diſpence at ſuch a time, a Man for all manner of Diſcretion, and it had ill becom'd me to have pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerv'd ſo much near ſo Beautiful a Perſon. Yet I did not drive my rude<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs too far neither, and <hi>Thereſia,</hi> (who had more of fear then I had of hold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs,) was quit of it, for ſome ſmall Stealths, which ſhe Revenged with Scratches.</p>
            <pb n="70" facs="tcp:47240:42"/>
            <p>The <hi>Duke</hi> and the <hi>Dutcheſs,</hi> having chang'd their Entertainements, they likewiſe alter'd their Diſcourſe; the <hi>Duke</hi> did preſently ask his Wife if ſhe was well pleas'd with her Miſtake.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>It will be your fault only if I am not,</hi> reply'd the <hi>Dutcheſs; but it is certain, that if you continue in your ſlights to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards me, another ſhall gain by it.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>That others (with whom you do ſo whreaten me,) can be no other then the Lord</hi> N. reply'd the <hi>Duke; If it were not He</hi> reply'd the <hi>Dutcheſs,</hi> (riſing to be gone,) <hi>It ſhould be another; But I will confeſs to you,</hi> (added ſhe, moving forwards,) <hi>that he ſhall always be prefer'd to any other when ever you give me an occaſion for it.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>They being then got at a further diſtance, we heard not any thing fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of their diſcourſe; So when <hi>The<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſia,</hi> who fear'd remaining alone with me, after what I had already done, riſing alſo, <hi>Are you not</hi> ſaid ſhe, <hi>the moſt rude of all Men, thus to prevail up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on my goodneſs, and to have ſo little of
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:47240:42"/>reſpect for me, who you ſee could not find in my heart to mind you?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Rather ſay, Madam,</hi> I anſwered, <hi>that I am oblig'd unto that danger which was equal to us both; And what danger</hi> reply'd ſhe? <hi>I neither fear the</hi> Duke, <hi>nor the</hi> Dutcheſs.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>I fear them as little as you do,</hi> I re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply'd, <hi>but it is probable that you would not have had the</hi> Dutcheſs <hi>to know, that you were ſo near her Husband, nor that the</hi> Duke <hi>ſhould think me ſo near his Miſtreſs.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thereſia</hi> having Highly defended her ſelf on that point, and making uſe of the ſame Reaſons againſt me; there happened a pleaſant diſpute betwixt us, which at laſt did terminate in rail<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lery on all that had happened to us both that Night, without any further explication on either ſide.</p>
            <p>In this manner we rejoined the company, where we found the <hi>Duke</hi> and the <hi>Dutcheſs,</hi> who doubtleſs be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing concern'd after us, were not a lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle ſurpris'd to ſee us come in together,
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:47240:43"/>not knowing whether we had not had the ſame fortune, that they had met with.</p>
            <p>All the reſt of that Evening, the <hi>Duke</hi> did appear very Diſcontented, and the <hi>Dutcheſs</hi> had her Eyes inceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſantly upon us; while, as if we had been agreed to make them both very uneaſy; <hi>Thereſia</hi> and I, affect to be of great Intelligence together, and we did continually Whiſper in one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers Ears, Laughing at their Coſt. So that the whole Court, that had al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways ſeen us of very contrary Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mours, were much ſurpris'd to ſee us on the ſuddain ſo well agreed, and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertaining one another with ſo much familiarity before the <hi>Duke.</hi> The Feaſt, which was then all ours, laſted not much longer; The Maſter of it having great reaſon to conclude it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the time, which he had deſigned it ſhould.</p>
            <p>After which every one having taken the way to the City, I took leave of <hi>Thereſia,</hi> who put her in the <hi>Dutcheſs's</hi>
               <pb n="73" facs="tcp:47240:43"/>Coach with whom ſhe had come thi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; and the <hi>Duke</hi> who was to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>company them, did not, but came to ask me room in mine.</p>
            <p>I did receive that Honour as I ought, but I did ſoon perceive to what it tended; and after we had been ſome time without ſpeaking.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>I muſt needs confeſs, My Lord,</hi> ſaid he, in a ſlighting manner, whi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>h did ſufficiently expreſs, with what a Paſſion his mind was poſſes'd, <hi>that for a young Man, you are very knowing, and that your love of indifferency has had no bad ſucceſs. There are none but for you now at Court, and your vanity extends ſo far, as to carry your deſigns on Perſons to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards whom you ought not ſo much as to lift up your Eyes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>I know not, my Lord,</hi> I reply'd, <hi>in what it has ever appeard, that I have loſt that reſpect which I owe you.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>That buſineſs</hi> anſwer'd he, <hi>has not need of any further clearing; what I tell you is ſufficient to put you in mind of your duty, it is time for you to re-enter into
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:47240:44"/>it; you are Young, I have ſome conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations for the Family whence you came, without that it is like, that I had not acted with all the moderation that I do at preſent; But abuſe not any of it, and make good uſe of this advice that I give you.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>I am very unhappy, My Lord,</hi> I re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply'd, <hi>thus to incur your diſpleaſure; but more that I know not by what means I am fallen into that misfortune; all that I can do, is to depart the Court; and if you deſire it, I will quit the Kingdom al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo, rather then give you the least diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiet.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thoſe ways that make ſuch noiſe, are not convenient,</hi> (anſwer'd he,) <hi>when you know what it is that I deſire of you, do it, and then, when you think good to be gone, you may, without giving any intimation of the cauſe thereof.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Converſation went no further, we remained all the reſt of the time in ſilence, until we came to the Palace, where he told me again, <hi>that I ſhould think on the advice which he had given
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:47240:44"/>me.</hi> But I had no ſooner quitted him, that ſeeing him take the way to the <hi>Dutcheſs's</hi> Appartment, whence I did not think that he would come forth again that night, that I went to <hi>The<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſias</hi> Lodgings, being impatient to learn what Entertainment ſhe had had with the <hi>Duke.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I found her undreſſing, and ſhe no ſooner did ſee me, but that ſhe told me in a Languiſhing ſtrain, that the <hi>Dutcheſs</hi> had given her an Intire Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vertiſement, and that now ſhe did be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve her more Jealous of me then of the <hi>Duke;</hi> all her buſineſs having been to learn where we two had met ſo as to return together; I alſo re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lated to her, all that had paſs'd in my Coach with the <hi>Duke;</hi> So that we were both Laughing heartily at it, when the <hi>Duke</hi> came into the Cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, which did very much ſurpriſe me.</p>
            <p>But <hi>Thereſia</hi> Laugh'd more lowd then before at it, which put him as much out of countenance, as I had
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:47240:45"/>been, who had no other thoughts but of retiring as I did perſonally.</p>
            <p>I did well imagine that this laſt ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſe, would make an end of placing me ill in the <hi>Dukes</hi> opinion.</p>
            <p>Therefore I did deſign not to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear at Court all the next day, fear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, as he was very haſtey, that in ſome ſuddain action he ſhould expreſs his reſentments againſt me.</p>
            <p>But I was ſcarce out of my Bed the next Morning, that one of his Gentlemen came to call me, as from him.</p>
            <p>I went into a Gallery where he ſtaid for me, and after he had receiv'd me with ſuch a cold Air, as did ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ently ſhew how he forc'd himſelf; <hi>I did believe Lord</hi> N. ſaid he, <hi>that I had ſufficiently given you to underſtand how far my nicety extended in reſpect of ſome Perſons, and I know not if it is that you would have me to expreſs my ſelf in that manner, that ſuch a contempt as you make of what I ſay to you, does de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="77" facs="tcp:47240:45"/>
            <p>
               <hi>You did only mention to me, my Lord,</hi> ſaid I, <hi>ſuch Perſons towards whom I ought not to lift up my Eyes, and I did not believe that that command did ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend ſo far, as on all kind of Perſons, and that I ought not to look on any body; eſpecially when you could not imagin that I ſhould have any deſign in it.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Whether I have ſpoken to you of it or not,</hi> (reply'd he, in a lowder voice) <hi>you know ſufficiently thoſe Perſons, in which I pretended to have ſome Interest, and if I find you there again; I would not adviſe you to carry it off without Laughing; for it would be Dangerous for any Perſon whatſoever to Laugh in the Court at my Coſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>You being not in the Chamber, My Lord,</hi> I anſwered him mildly, <hi>when we began to Laugh—No no,</hi> interrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted he, <hi>what I ſay is ſufficient, it is not good to play the Jeſter with me here; You forget your ſelf; ſee where you are, and you will know what you owe me.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Upon this he left me haſtily, not hearkning any longer to what I ſaid.</p>
            <pb n="78" facs="tcp:47240:46"/>
            <p>This Treatment did ſeem ſomething harſh, though I had deſerv'd part of it, and I judging that I ſhould not paſs my time very well in that Court, being thus out with the <hi>Duke,</hi> who would certainly have my ſteps ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerv'd, I took the reſolution to be gone.</p>
            <p>But in the condition that I found my heart at that time, it was almoſt impoſſible to get his conſent to leave ſo ſoon that Country; it was not now the <hi>Dutcheſs</hi> that did detain it only, It was <hi>Thereſia</hi> alſo, for whom I had always had a greater inclination; who notwithſtanding the cauſe that I had given her that Night of Anger againſt me, had not treated me with all the rigour that I might have expected from her. And even the manner af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter which ſhe had return'd with me to the Company; and that we had af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter that diſcours'd together, had not any thing in it, which gave me not hopes that ſhe had no mind to hate me long.</p>
            <pb n="79" facs="tcp:47240:46"/>
            <p>Finally, ſo many other things which came into my mind, and ſo many Amorous <hi>Ideas</hi> which I had upon all thoſe liberties which I had taken with her, having render'd me more paſſio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate then ever.</p>
            <p>I chang'd the reſolution which I had taken of abſolutely quitting that King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, to an eight days abſence from Court, to give way to the <hi>Dukes</hi> Anger, and to learn in what diſpoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of heart my two Ladies were, and how they would take my abſence; I did think my ſelf oblig'd to give them notice of my departure, and this is the Note which I Writ to the <hi>Dutcheſs.</hi>
            </p>
            <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
               <body>
                  <p>
                     <hi>IF I had not fear'd diſturbing the joy of your being ſo well reconcil'd to your Husband, I could not have hindred my ſelf from ſeeing you, and of taking leave of you at my Retiring from Court, notwithſtanding any orders to the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary. But I muſt let you enjoy in peace the happineſs of poſſeſſing him, Yet I fear it will not laſt long, and that there
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:47240:47"/>will happen ſome Amorons relapſes that may ſteal him from you a ſecond time; Then you will have ſome thoughts of me, and perhaps wiſh me near you again. Though it is a greater Honour to be at any time ſerviſable to you on any account, yet it is but an ill requital to have the whole misfortune of the adventure, to fall wholly upon me, at the ſame time that I expected to be over com'd with favour.</hi>
                  </p>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
               <body>
                  <head>I ſent her this Note by a truſty Agent, and this is what I Writ to <hi>Thereſia.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>IF I had any hopes of Living plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſantly in this Court, I would not leave it; but it being forbid me to ſee you, and what is more; to laugh with you, what pleaſure can I receive in it? or rather how could I forbear thoſe things, but by timely withdrawing my ſelf from all the occaſions of doing them? I did par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tly gueſs that ſo much good fortune in one day could not laſt long, of which had I been as certain, I would have made better uſe, in declaring to you a Secret
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:47240:47"/>which concerns my Life that you ſhould know it, but that it is of too dangerous a Nature to commit to Paper; To what ſhould I not be concern'd if it were known? I ſhall tell it to none but you, becauſe that th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>re is none but you that ought to know it.</hi>
                  </p>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>Theſe two Notes being Writ and ſent, I got on Horſe back, and I reti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red my ſelf with a Lord that was a Friend of mine, ſome ten Viles from the City. Where the next day, I re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiv'd anſwer to both my Letters, and this is that of the <hi>Dutcheſs</hi>'s.</p>
            <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
               <body>
                  <p>
                     <hi>I have been ſtrangely ſurpris'd at your abſence, but the ſorrow that I feel for it Surpaſſes that; you little know what paſſes in my Heart, when you ſpeak to me of joy; I am no longer capable of any, but when I ſee you, and He you ſpeak of, has bethought himſelf too late of his duty. You have made ſo good uſe of his negligence, not to ſay more, that there is no room left for him in my Heart. It fell very unlucky that ſhe poſſeſt your place
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:47240:48"/>at</hi> Roggio Regale; <hi>but where were you? Were you as unfortunate as I was? But why ſais I, unfortunate, after ſeeing your return ſo well accompanyed. Oh! Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, it is poſſible that that Creature muſt be the cauſe of all my Miſeries? Farwell, I ſhall have no reſt till I ſee you, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore return with the ſooneſt; there will be ways found to ſee one another, and not be known.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <closer>
                     <salute>Farwel,</salute>
                  </closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
               <body>
                  <head>Two hours after this I receiv'd that from <hi>Thereſia,</hi> which was in theſe Terms.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>THoſe Perſons know not what they do, who would deprive me from the Innocent pleaſure of Langhing with you; I have an heart wholly addicted to mutiny, and at the leaſt oppoſition that it finds, it has no greater delight than to bend it ſelf againſt thoſe obſtacles. It were fine indeed, to hinder us from Laughing and ſeeing one another; Do but return, that we may have that ſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction, in ſpite of all; I am almoſt dead
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:47240:48"/>with longing to know the ſecret which you mention, and if it be ſuch a one as I imagine, I promiſe you before-hand, that none ſhall know it but my ſelf.</hi>
                  </p>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>This commerce having laſted ſeven or eight days, during which the ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der confidence that was between <hi>The<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſia</hi> and I, did daily increaſe my af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections, and the Hearts correſpon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dency which I had with the <hi>Dutcheſs,</hi> did very much decay; of two Letters that ſhe did Write to me, I made but one anſwer; whereas <hi>Thereſia,</hi> had al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways two Letters from me, for one of hers; and I did ſo imploy my ſelf of tenderneſs, with this, that I had ſcarce any thing left for the other, the which ſhe was not long without perceiving, and attributing to abſence that which was the meer eflect of an incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtancy. At laſt ſhe Writ to me this Note.</p>
            <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
               <body>
                  <p>
                     <hi>IF abſence was to you ſo hard a thing as you ſay it is, you would do more
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:47240:49"/>then you do to ſee us again. Theſe rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons which you aledge in juſtification of it, proceeds not from a very paſſionate Man, pray, not ſo much reſervedneſs, and ſomewhat more of Love, and then you will find nothing difficult; This you would know, did you Love as you ſhould. I have a thouſand things to tell you, but they are kind reproaches which I will make you in Perſon; Be this night in the Garden of the Pallace, I ſend you the Key of the Port-Gate, I ſhall ſtay for you there, from twelve at night till two.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <closer>
                     <salute>Farwel.</salute>
                  </closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>The Paſſion which I had had for the <hi>Dutcheſs,</hi> did awaken again at the lecture of this Letter; and notwithſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding all the love that I had for <hi>There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſia,</hi> I could not refuſe ſuch a rendez<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vous as that.</p>
            <p>I was ſo in Love with thoſe kind of adventurs, that I would have quit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted all to have ſuch an Entertainment for a Lady.</p>
            <pb n="85" facs="tcp:47240:49"/>
            <p>I therefore prepar'd my ſelf for that, and parted from that place where I was, at a convenient hour to get to the Garden at the appointed time; but I made ſuch haſte in the Impatiency I was, that it was but Eleven of the Clock when I found my ſelf at the Gate; I had but one Man with me, whom I caus'd to wait with my Horſe at ſome diſtance from thence, in a very private place. I did open the Gate, and I gently advanc'd from one Alley into another, it being early enough yet to meet with People there; as I did hear ſome walking, I hid my ſelf between two Hedges, to ſee who it was, for it ſeem'd to me as if they were comming my way; At laſt I heard a voice that ſpoke very low, but as they ſtill did draw nearer me, to reſt themſelves on ſome Seats that were not far from me; I was near enough to diſcern that it was the <hi>Dukes</hi> voice. I did not doubt but that he was diſcourſing with <hi>The<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſia;</hi> and Jealouſie, as well as ſome curioſity, inſenſſibly ingaging me to
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:47240:50"/>draw nearer ſtill; I at laſt creept ſo cloſe to them as to underſtand what they ſaid; <hi>But what is then the Cauſe,</hi> (ſaid <hi>Thereſia,) of his abſence from Court? You know it, Madam,</hi> reply'd the <hi>Duke, but to free you from the trouble of asking it me again; I will tell you that he has treſpaſs'd a little too much upon my houn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty; I Love you, Madam,</hi> continu'd he. <hi>My Lord,</hi> (reply'd <hi>Thereſia,</hi> Interrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting him,) <hi>and is that the cauſe of his diſgrace? And have you any cauſe on that account to complain of either of us? But too much,</hi> reply'd the <hi>Duke, You ſtrangely ſurprize me,</hi> anſwer'd <hi>Thereſia, and you will much oblige me, to let me know, in what it has appear'd that the Lord</hi> N. <hi>has ever made one ſtep only in favour of me.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>I am but too well experimented in thoſe things,</hi> (reply'd the <hi>Duke) to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come the Interpreter of his actions, and grant that I had deceiv'd my ſelf, you take too much his Intereſts, to prove that, he is wholly innocent.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="87" facs="tcp:47240:50"/>
            <p>This converſation which had ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing in it very pleaſing to me, was growing to go warm in good earneſt; when that the ruffling of ſome Petti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coats, which were heard at the end of the Alley, made the <hi>Duke</hi> to liſten that way; and fearing leaſt it ſhould be the <hi>Dutcheſs,</hi> that came to eſpy him, he intreated <hi>Thereſia</hi> to hide her ſelf in the Hedge, and ſtay'd till his Wife came up to ſpeak to her.</p>
            <p>By good fortune, the <hi>Dutcheſs</hi> had taken along with her a Woman, in whom ſhe did conſide, having not Courage enough to venture ſingly in the Garden at that time of the Night, and perceiving the <hi>Duke,</hi> ſhe did at firſt take him for me, which might have ſpoyl'd all, had not his Impatiency ſo tranſported him, that he aroſe and go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing towards her<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>What! Madam,</hi> (ſaid he,) <hi>will you never give me any reſt? What is it you deſire? What come you here for? Is it nor Bed time with you yet?</hi> The <hi>Dutcheſs</hi> was ſo ſurpris'd and confounded at the <hi>Dukes</hi> voice,
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:47240:51"/>that ſhe knew not at firſt what to an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer; But fearing leaſt her ſilence ſhould betray her, or that at leaſt it would make him to diſtruſt ſomewhat of the truth, ſhe told him with a trem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bling voice, <hi>That ſhe was come with no other deſign, than to walk; which if it troubled him, ſhe would retire into her Chamber.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Yes, Madam,</hi> reply'd he, (giving her his hand,) <hi>and you will much ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lige me not to ſtir from thence at ſuch hours as theſe;</hi> and upon that, he led her back himſelf to be the more ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure.</p>
            <p>Mean time I was very loath to loſe ſo fair an opportunity, and being not very far from <hi>Thereſia,</hi> I did riſe to come to her, but ſhe no ſooner heard the noiſe which I made, that ſhe got out of the Hedge, and began to run away, I follow'd calling ſoftly to her, for fear of being heard by the <hi>Duke,</hi> who could not yet be very far, but ſhe ſtill did run on, till I did overtake her, and let her know who I was; <hi>Oh!</hi>
               <pb n="89" facs="tcp:47240:51"/>
               <hi>my Lord,</hi> (ſaid ſhe, quite out of Breath) <hi>in what a Fright have you put me? I am half dead with it;</hi> after which, ſhe ſate her ſelf on the Graſs, to compoſe her a little.</p>
            <p>While I was Kneeling before her, I did ask Pardon for the trouble that I had given her, for which I was ſo ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry that I would have repair'd it with my Life.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>I will forgive you,</hi> (ſaid ſhe,) <hi>if you will tell me what you were come here to do? It was my happy fate, Madam,</hi> (I reply'd,) <hi>that did conduct me here, to be Charm'd with the Honour that you do me, in concerning your ſelf ſo much for me. You have then heard the diſcourſes which I have had with the</hi> Duke, (an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer'd ſhe,) <hi>I have not told him</hi> (ſhe continu'd,) <hi>half that I had to ſay to him on that account; But that is not the buſineſs now in hand; I only ask you what was your deſign? And if it is not for Love of the</hi> Dutcheſs <hi>that you have left your ſolitude; for in all probab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity ſhe came to ſeek you, and this was
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:47240:52"/>an aſſignation which ſhe had given you, or I am much miſtaken.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>I Love</hi> Thereſia <hi>too well, to conceal the truth from her, and thought this was no better, then ſacrificing of the</hi> Dut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheſs <hi>to her; I rather choſe that the one ſhould reproach me a little with Treachery, than the other that I had not been ſincere to her in an occaſion of this nature; I therefore told her the truth,</hi> (adding,) <hi>that the ſucceſs had been more favourable to me than I durst have expected, ſince that I had been ſo happy as to meet with her; You had been much more happy,</hi> (anſwer'd he,) <hi>if you had met with the</hi> Dutcheſs; <hi>It was in my power to do it,</hi> (I anſwer'd,) <hi>and I could have prevented her comming up, in running to meet her, ſo as that ſhe had not come ſo near you, as to be known. But how can it be,</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply'd <hi>Thereſia, that you being Charm'd with the Beauty of a Lady, for whoſe Love you thus expoſe your Life, that you ſhould neglect her ſo much when you are ſo near? If you had not been here,</hi> I re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply'd, <hi>ſhe had not been ſo neglected, but
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:47240:52"/>where e're you are, I cannot think of any other Perſon; (What you tell me now</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply'd ſhe,) <hi>is ſomething difficult to be be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liev'd; and ſhould I require from you ſome Aſſurances of it, I think that I ſhould puzle you.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>I am ready, Madam,</hi> (anſwer'd I,) <hi>to give it you; And my Heart, who did Sigh for you, from the very moment that I did ſee you first, and that has never ceas'd doing ſo, whereſoever otherwiſe I my cares and ſteps have been imploy'd, ſhall give you ſuch proofs thereof, that you ſhall have no longer cauſe to doubt it.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>I am very ſenſible, my Lord,</hi> (ſaid ſhe, after a little pauſe,) <hi>that I am weak enough to be perſwaded into that belief, had I not before my Eyes an example which ought to make me miſtrust you.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>You would be too unjuſt,</hi> (I anſwered,) <hi>ſhould you condemn me on thoſe appear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ances. No, I ſhall not condemn you,</hi> (an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer'd ſhe,) <hi>but I will examine your Heart a little better yet, there's enough for this time; For in the fears that I
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:47240:53"/>am in of the</hi> Duke, <hi>I cannot tell you half the things which I have to ſay to you.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I did endeavour to obey her, but in that impatiency that I was to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude this converſation, having ask'd of her <hi>If that could not ſee her in pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate;</hi> ſhe told me, <hi>That it would be very difficult, by reaſon that the</hi> Duke <hi>did obſerve her continually after ſuch a man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, that ſhe liv'd like a Slave.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I Sighed upon this, and told her, <hi>That if ſhe pleas'd, I would meet her the next day in the ſame place;</hi> but ſhe an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer'd, <hi>That there was too much of dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger in it for me; And that ſhe ſhould fear on her part both the</hi> Duke <hi>and the</hi> Dutcheſs.</p>
            <p>Finally, after I had intreated her to tell me her ſelf, what happy moment there might be for me to entertain her in, more at large; ſhe told me, <hi>That if I would stay till ſhe had retir'd her ſelf with the</hi> Duke, <hi>ſhe might perhaps find out ſome means to return to me again;</hi> Upon which I did caſt my ſelf at her
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:47240:53"/>Feet, and kiſs'd a thouſand times one of her fair Hands; but ſhe preſently caus'd me to retire, becauſe ſhe heard the <hi>Duke</hi> comming, ſhe tenderly preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing my hand with both her hands, as I took leave of her.</p>
            <p>The impatient Amorous <hi>Duke</hi> gave me but juſt time ſufficient to hide my ſelf through the haſte that he made to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards <hi>Thereſia;</hi> and very much con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern'd at the intereſt that ſhe had in my affairs, there being no intereſt that can proceed from indifferency; he pr<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently began the diſcourſe on the ſame Chapter.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>If,</hi> ſaid he, <hi>you have any conſiderati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on in the World for me, you must no more mention the Lord</hi> N. <hi>to me, and you muſt likewiſe forbid him of ſeeing of you; As to no longer ſpeaking of him to you, that will not be difficult for me to do,</hi> reply'd <hi>Thereſia, but I cannot for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bid him ſeeing of me; It would too much concern my reputation; What would he think of it?</hi> continu'd ſhe, <hi>that you are Jealous of him? or it may be that</hi> I <hi>Lov'd
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:47240:54"/>him; Do you not put me, my Lord,</hi> (added ſhe,) <hi>on ſuch obſervances; You have already but too much expos'd me to publick talk, and I will not make an end of ruining my ſelf.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Well, Madam,</hi> (reply'd the <hi>Duke,</hi> with ſome paſſion,) <hi>I ſhall forbid him my ſelf, ſince that you will not. That were the way,</hi> (reply'd <hi>Thereſia,</hi>) <hi>to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe my deſign of ſeeing him; That you ſay,</hi> (reply'd the <hi>Duke,</hi>) <hi>is the way to give you the greater deſire of ſeeing him; Yes doubtleſs,</hi> (reply'd <hi>Thereſia,</hi>) <hi>and I do confeſs to you, that that manner of Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving to which I am daily reduc'd by you, is very cruel, it will at laſt come to paſs, that I ſhall be compel'd to be Lock'd up like a Priſoner in my Chamber, as in a manner I am already, without the liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of ſeeing any body; Rather ſay, Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam,</hi> (interrupted the <hi>Duke,</hi>) <hi>that you have not began to take notice of this cruel Life, which others would not call ſo; But ſince the Lord</hi> N's. <hi>abſence, that whereſoever he is not, you will think your ſelf uneaſy, and reſtrained; and that in
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:47240:54"/>fine, to gain your favour, I must my ſef<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> invite him again to Court, and if you pleaſe conduct him to your Appartment. It is pitty he hears you not,</hi> (reply'd <hi>The<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſia,</hi>) <hi>and I do believe that if he did but know the good Offices that you render him towards me, that he would return you thanks for them; For, to tell you the truth, to act as you do, would not be a means to drive a man from my heart; If he were there, it would rather be. Yes, it would,</hi> (interrupted the <hi>Duke</hi> in a paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, having not the patience to let her make an end,) <hi>be the way to make you Love him. This is already done,</hi> (continu'd he,) <hi>but I ſhall prevent him, for enjoying ſuch an happineſs. It is not from this day that I know you to be Paſſionate,</hi> (reply'd <hi>Thereſia,</hi> riſing to be gone,) <hi>but if you would believe me,</hi> (continu'd ſhe,) <hi>you would not be too ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſty on that account; I ſhall not take Councel of you</hi> (reply'd the <hi>Duke;</hi>) <hi>and I do engage, that before it be Twenty-four hours longer, I ſhall rid my ſelf of a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon that gives me too much vexation,
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:47240:55"/>not to invite me to Baniſh him out of the Kingdom. And I engage to you,</hi> (re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply'd <hi>Thereſia,</hi>) <hi>that before Twenty-four hours are paſs'd, I ſhall be no longer in this Court. That's the way,</hi> (reply'd the <hi>Duke,</hi>) <hi>to make me drive more home my reſentments; Drive or not,</hi> (reply'd ſhe,) <hi>this is what I will perform by to Mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By this time, they were got too far from me, to hear any more of their diſcourſes; neither did I think it con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venient to follow them, after what I had heard; It is certain, that there ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver was any pleaſure like to that which this converſation did give me; and that if Love had not engag'd me alrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy to give my heart unto the Beauti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful <hi>Thereſia;</hi> the bare knowledge of what ſhe had done that night for me, had oblig'd me to Love her moſt paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſionately; There wanted nothing to make me perfectly happy, but the ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfacton of ſeeing her again one mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment only, before I went from thence, as ſhe had promis'd me; but it appear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:47240:55"/>to me too much happineſs at once; Yet ſhe out-went my hopes, and I did ſee her return, even before I expected it, by reaſon that the Converſation which ſhe had had with the <hi>Duke</hi> in the Garden, being not pleaſant, as to invite him to the continuation of it in her Chamber, he had retired as full of Jealouſy and Spight, as ever was a Lover.</p>
            <p>I did run towards her, ſo ſoon as I perceived her, and caſting my ſelf at her Feet; <hi>What is it that I do not require of you, Madam?</hi> (ſaid I,) <hi>after that good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, which you have expreſſed towards me this Night, had I a thouſand Lives, though I ſhould expoſe them all for you, I could not repay ſo many Graces and Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Alaſs, my Lord,</hi> (reply'd ſhe, cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing me to riſe,) <hi>I fear very much, that on the contrary, I have given you cauſe to hate me, I am return'd but only to tell you, with what rage againſt you, the</hi> Duke <hi>has left me; and at the ſame time to intreat you, not to wait the effects of
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:47240:56"/>his Paſſion, but to depart this very night from theſe Dominions. I, Madam,</hi> ſaid I, (interrupting her,) <hi>go out of this Kingdom, to leave in the hands of a moſt violent man, and of a Rival, all that is deareſt to me in the World, a Lady that has laid a ſide all other conſiderations to take my part, and to ſhew that I was more then indifferent to her.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Yes, my Lord,</hi> (reply'd ſhe,) <hi>I have done ſo, and I can farther ſay, that I have done nothing in that, but what my heart has allowed of; And that if you have found me according to your heart the firſt time that you did ſee me, I have not found you unworthy of mine from the very first moment that I ſaw you, and that if ever any thing did vex me in all my life, it was when you gave the King unto the</hi> Dutcheſs, <hi>which in truth, I expected for my ſelf.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>And you had had it; that Ring,</hi> (an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer'd I,) <hi>if it had been the Choice of my heart, which did then ſufficiently draw me towards you; But the</hi> Duke—<hi>Yes, the</hi> Duke, (interrupted ſhe,) <hi>always con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:47240:56"/>to my happineſs, will be the cauſe of my Death.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>The cauſe of your Death, (Madam,</hi> ſaid I,) <hi>I it is not now time to extend your ſelf on this Theme,</hi> (reply'd ſhe,) <hi>you muſt think of returning your ſelf with the ſoo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt, into ſome place of ſafety, that I may have no more to fear as to your Life.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>You, to fear in regard of my Life, Madam,</hi> (I reply'd with an Air whol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly tranſported;) <hi>know, that if it must be ſav'd, it cannot be but without you, and that I ſhould ſooner deliver my ſelf up into the</hi> Dukes <hi>hands, than abandon you.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>If I had not my Honour to mind, my Lord,</hi> (reply'd ſhe ſighing) <hi>I find a ſufficient willingneſs in me to follow you, and to deſire no other <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ortune then yours, but the Honour of a Perſon of my Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity</hi>—</p>
            <p>
               <hi>What Danger is there in this, as to your Honour,</hi> (ſaid I interrupting and Embracing her, with all that Tender<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs that I had,) <hi>with a man that gives you his Faith from this very moment.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="99" facs="tcp:47240:57"/>
            <p>She remain'd ſome time after this without anſwering, and preſently leaning gently on me. <hi>If you give it me,</hi> (ſaid ſhe, with a languiſhing voice) <hi>Will you keep it then?</hi> I redoubling all the proteſtations, that a man in ſuch a Paſſion as I was, could utter.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>It is ſufficient,</hi> (ſaid ſhe,) <hi>I am ſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fi'd; let us retire, and do what is moſt convenient, to ſhelter us from the</hi> Dukes <hi>violent temper, for in the condition I am at preſent, I do not find my ſelf capable of giving you any Councel.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I did then propoſe to her, to Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>barque our ſelves that very night, and to retire into the Eccleſiaſtick Juriſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diction; which ſhe did approve of: and having at the ſame time turn'd to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards the Gate of the Port of which I had the Key; We had ſcarce made ſome ſteps towards it, but that we perceiv'd the <hi>Dutcheſs</hi> coming from behind ſome Trees, who had heard all that we had ſaid, and who throwing her ſelf upon <hi>Thereſia,</hi> to prevent her from following me; She call'd me a
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:47240:57"/>thouſand times Perfidious, and Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cherous, while I was endeavouring to make her let go her Rival; which ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving done, at laſt, ſhe cry'd out ſo loud that the <hi>Duke,</hi> who was not far from thence, and who in that deſpair that he was gone to Bed, did think of no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing leſs then ſleep, not knowing what was become of the <hi>Dutcheſs,</hi> did not believe that ſhe was return'd into the Garden without ſome deſign; So that running thither with Five or Six Muſqueteers, and as many Halberteers of his Guard; He came there at that time, that the <hi>Dutcheſs</hi> was making of that noiſe; and preſently falling up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on me, calling me by all the Infamous names that he could think on.</p>
            <p>I had made him to paſs by ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing of his fury, though I had nothing but a ſhort Sword and my Dagger, if he had not been accompany'd with all thoſe Halberteers, who after they had wounded me in two places, they knock'd me down with a blow which I receiv'd on my head, which caus'd
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:47240:58"/>
               <hi>Thereſia</hi> to fall into a Swound, who was ſeconding of me as much as ſhe could, and who ſaw the Blow given me.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Dutcheſs,</hi> who in ſpight of all the Anger that ſhe had againſt me, had alſo declar'd on my ſide; ſeeing me aſſaulted by ſo many, did think me Dead with that blow, and after that ſhe had furiouſly flown out againſt the <hi>Duke;</hi> She took my Sword which ſhe found on the Ground, and had like to have Kill'd with it the laſt that had wounded me, there being no ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>travagancy that ſhe did not commit; threatning her Husband with Death, to revenge mine.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Duke,</hi> whoſe fury was ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing appeas'd at the ſight of my body lying on the ground, knowing well what parties my Parents would be for him to deal with, who would ask him an account of my Bloud, even to the very laſt drop, having his mind whol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly taken up, with all thoſe troubleſom thoughts, did not mind what his Wife
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:47240:58"/>ſaid; and after he had given order to ſome of his People to Carry me into <hi>Caſtle-Novo,</hi> and immediatly to run for Surgeons, to ſee if there was any hopes of life left in me; But gave charge to others to take care of <hi>There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſia,</hi> and taking upon himſelf the care of the <hi>Dutcheſs,</hi> he led her back into her Appartment.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Duke</hi> did what he could to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent this buſineſs from breaking out; but in two or three days, the whole Court did know it.</p>
            <p>Is was diverſly diſcours'd, every one according to his fancy, there be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing no Perſon that could imagine, how I had happened to be between thoſe two Ladies, and why the <hi>Dutcheſs,</hi> (of whom there was a rumour that I was in good Intelligence with,) had cry'd out after me in that manner; and yet afterwards took my part againſt the <hi>Duke.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In fine, never did buſineſs give ſo much cauſe of reaſoning in all <hi>Italy</hi> as that did, without being well under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood;
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:47240:59"/>
               <hi>Thereſia's</hi> Friends did immedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ately come to fetch her home; whence preſently after, News was brought that ſhe was dead, either with Grief, or with Poiſon.</p>
            <p>As for me, my Wounds being nor Mortal, I was judg'd paſt all danger at the very firſt dreſſing; and ſome days after in a condition to ſtir a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broad; But the <hi>Duke</hi> who would up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold what he had done; and what was more, call me to an account for the at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt which I had committed in the night ſeaſon, in his own Pallace, againſt his Life and Honour, accuſing me of both.</p>
            <p>He cauſed me to be under greater reſtraint than ever, in <hi>Caſtle-Novo,</hi> without the Liberty of ſeeing any body; ſo that he imform'd the Court of <hi>Spain,</hi> as he pleas'd himſelf, of all that paſs'd, and if any of my Friends did write concerning it, to oblige me, it was ſo weakly, and in ſuch obſcure terms, not knowing how the buſineſs had really paſt; that part of my Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lations,
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:47240:59"/>(who were pre-poſſeſt with the <hi>Dukes</hi> complaints,) were againſt me, and I had been abſolutely condemn'd, (if it were uſual to do ſo,) without hearing of both parties.</p>
            <p>I remain'd Six Months in this man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner in <hi>Caſtle-Novo,</hi> without the leaſt knowledge of any thing of my buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, daily wiſhing for Death; After that of <hi>Thereſia,</hi> which the <hi>Duke</hi> had been ſo cruel as to inform me of, not doubting but that it would be an ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition of troubles to me, which would conclude my Life.</p>
            <p>When one day, about Nine or Ten at Night, I ſaw come into my Cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber a kind of Servant, which I thought that I had formerly ſeen, but where I could not remember; He drew near me, and preſented me a Note; <hi>Do you not know</hi> Julia, <hi>my Lord?</hi> This was one of the <hi>Dutcheſſes</hi> Women, whom ſhe had made her confident, and who had diſguis'd her ſelf like a Serving-Man to bring me this Note from her. I open'd it, and found in it theſe Words.</p>
            <pb n="105" facs="tcp:47240:60"/>
            <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
               <body>
                  <p>
                     <hi>SO long as my Anger has laſted a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst you, I have hindred my Heart from Making its reſentments ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear, by thoſe reproaches that had juſt cauſe to make you. This was too great an advantage for you, and you know, what merited that treachery, which you have done me; But ſince that all my Anger is over, and that there is no more danger to fear, for my Heart, I let pity Act. It is not refus'd to the moſt indif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferent Perſons, and ſome it is to be al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low'd unto your Youth, were there none to ſpare for the misfortunes which you have drawn upon your ſelf; ſee what may be done for you, and you ſhall be ſerv'd in it; You have not given me o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vermuch cauſe for it; but when a Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon is throughly Generous, it is to this hight.</hi>
                  </p>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>What occaſion ſoever I had, to be very Angry with the <hi>Dutcheſs,</hi> on whom I did look on as the cauſe of all my misfortunes, this exceſs of bounty
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:47240:60"/>that ſhe expreſs'd towards me, when I did leaſt think of it, and when I ſtood moſt in need of ſuch a conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable aſſiſtance, did make an end of diſſipating a neſt of reſentments which were remaining in my Heart againſt her; And after that I had told <hi>Julia, That I would willingly have made an an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer to her Miſtreſs, but that I had not Pen, Ink, or Paper, and that it had always been refus'd me;</hi> ſhe promis'd to get me ſome the next day, by the means of two of my Guards, which the <hi>Dutcheſs</hi> had gain'd, after two Months endeavour, and that were with me Twenty-four hours every Week, which was from the hour of Twelve, till the next day at the ſame hour; So that it was abſolutely neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary, that my Letters ſhould be ready againſt that time, if I would have the ſame Guards to carry them.</p>
            <p>I promis'd that they ſhould; and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter that, having ask'd her ſome News of my concerns, ſhe ſatisfi'd me as well as ſhe could: But fearing to be ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pris'd
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:47240:61"/>with me, becauſe that all the Night I was hourly viſited in my Chamber, I gave her leave to retire, with a Thouſand Teſtimonies of ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledgments, to her Miſtreſs, of which I deſired her to give her an ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Julia</hi> returned, and the next Mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, I having been furniſhed by one of the Guards with all neceſſaries for Writing, I began with my Relations, unto whom I had divers things to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late; after which I Writ a Note to return the <hi>Dutcheſs</hi> thanks, and to recommend my Letters to her care; This is the contents of that Note.</p>
            <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
               <body>
                  <p>
                     <hi>IT is moſt certain, Madam, that your bounty does as much ſurpriſe me, as I am depreſs'd with confuſion; the uſing me after ſo generous a manner as you do, is the way to puniſh me more ſeverely then with giving me all the names of Traitor, Perjur'd, or even my Death; others there are that have betray'd as I have, and perhaps with leſs reaſon, yet
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:47240:61"/>my crime is greater then ever yet was committed becauſe that I have offended that Perſon, which in the World did the leaſt deſerve it; If I could repair it with my Death, you ſhould not remain long unſatisfied? for as in all likelyhood, I ſhall not get out of Priſon ſuddenly; I hope from the aſſiſtance of my ſorrow, not to Languiſh much longer in this place; I take the liberty to intruſt to you ſome Letters, for my relations, in which you will ſee Madam, ſuch a relation, as I ought to Pen it, on the occaſion of my misfortunes, and this ſhall be the last favour which I ſhall require of you, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſting to you that I ſhall not dye with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the regret of having been forc'd by a neceſſity much ſtronger then that of duty, to abandon a Perſon, whoſe eſteem I did not diſcern, no more then that tenderneſs that ſhe had for me.</hi>
                  </p>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>The <hi>Dutcheſs</hi> could not read my Note without melting into Tears, and though I had left open thoſe Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters that went into <hi>Spain,</hi> ſhe would
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:47240:62"/>not read them; but having ſeal'd them up, ſhe had them both ſecretly and ſecurely convey'd to <hi>Madrid.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>From that time I did begin to find ſome comfort through the <hi>Dutcheſses</hi> kind Aſſiſtance; who did not fail on all occaſions, to give me ſome notice of all that paſs'd, and daily to Write to me, more kindly then the other; it may be gueſt at, by this Note which ſhe ſent to me after a Bleeding.</p>
            <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
               <body>
                  <p>I <hi>have been this day indiſpos'd, and have caus'd my ſelf to be let Bloud in the left Arm, to leave the other at liberty to Write to you; I ſhould not gain much in depriving my ſelf, for a little pain that I feel, from that ſatisfaction which alone does cure me of divers Evils; I feel all yours, and I would do more then barely alleviate them; But ought I not to fear the effects of ingratitude, once again? Why can I not forget that you have been ſo? I ſhould be happy then, but how can that be, when you do not aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſist me in it? Ah! My Lord, how lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:47240:62"/>do you deſerve, that one ſhould have ſo much tenderneſs for you.</hi>
                  </p>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>I muſt confeſs, that in the ſad con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition that I was brought to, after ſeven Months of Impriſonment, in which time I had not ſeen any one, my ſorrows and afflictions did leave but little room for ſuch kind of Sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>timents; there was nothing but ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row in my Heart, I made the <hi>Dutcheſs</hi> this anſwer.</p>
            <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
               <body>
                  <p>I <hi>confeſs to you, Madam, that ſuch an unfortunate wretch as I am, do de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve ſome compaſſions, but nothing more, becauſe that I ſhould not be in a condition to return what I ſhould owe, to and other reſentments, that ſhould be had for me; If I were not Perfidious, I ſhould at least be ungrateful, which is yet a greater crime; your bounties are too large, not to reach my heart; but that heart is too much loaded with miſeries, to have wherewith to anſwer your boun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties. Permit me to dye, Madam, ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:47240:63"/>then thus to overcome me with fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour, which I never have deſerv'd, and of which I ſhall never render my ſelf worthy</hi>
                  </p>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>Theſe Letters of mine, which were more fill'd with complaints, then with tenderneſs, did not however leſs in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flame with love; The ſenſible <hi>Dut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheſs,</hi> who did Bathe them in her Tears at the Lecture of them. My Relations in <hi>Spain</hi> had receiv'd mine; but at Court, they were ſo prepoſſeſs'd to my prejudice, and the <hi>Dukes</hi> party was ſo great, that all the anſwer which I had, was, <hi>That it might be hop'd, they ſhould obtain from Court, to have me transfer'd to</hi> Madrid.</p>
            <p>But thoſe Court deliberations are ſuch tedious things, beſides the oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitions that would be made by the <hi>Dukes</hi> party; that as Powerful as were my Relations, and though they were never ſo dilligent, it was likely, that thoſe Afflictions, and that Melan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cholly which I had upon me, would
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:47240:63"/>Kill me, before that the order of this tranſportation ſhould be Arriv'd at <hi>Naples.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And of truth, in the midſt of all thoſe troubles that I was ſorrow'd with, I had rather have dyed then live; This was my condition, when one night, when it was thoſe two Guards turn, that the <hi>Dutcheſs</hi> had gain'd to watch me, after that they had inform'd me that that night they had nothing to ſay to me from her, which had plung'd me yet into a grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter forrow, I perceiv'd come into my Chamber a Cavalier, very well accou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred, who was Uſher'd in by a Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant, that did bear a Flambau before him.</p>
            <p>I was ſurpris'd to receive ſuch a vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſit at that hour of the night, and I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liev'd that it was not without ſome great conſequences; I aroſe from my Bed, on which I was ſeated, and ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vanced towards him, but he preſently running towards me, he did imbrace me with his Eyes full of Tears, which I
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:47240:64"/>I felt falling on my Cheeks; This acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on did ſurpriſe me more then the viſit, and I did not doubt but that it was ſome friend from <hi>Madrid,</hi> who had obtained from the <hi>Duke</hi> to ſee me; but what was my aſtoniſhment, when that having look'd on him, I found that it was the <hi>Dutcheſs,</hi> and ſhe that bore the Flombeau, <hi>Julia, What Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam, is it you,</hi> (ſaid I, going back two ſteps) <hi>thus to Honour me with this kind viſit, in ſuch a miſerable place as this is?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>It is not now time, my Lord,</hi> (an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer'd ſhe,) <hi>to examine that point of Honour, your liberty is the preſent buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs: See if you will receive it at my Hands, for it abſolutely depends on me.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Theſe ſorrows Madam,</hi> (I reply'd,) <hi>which I feel in this place, are ſo great, and I am detained in them with ſo much Juſtice, that I ſhould be excuſable, ſhould I receive that favour from my very Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies: much more from a Perſon, to whom I am ſo much oblig'd.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="114" facs="tcp:47240:64"/>
            <p>
               <hi>But do you know,</hi> (ſaid ſhe Sighing,) <hi>what is expected as a reward from this freedom?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>If that my Life,</hi> (I anſwered,) <hi>and all that belongs unto me.</hi>—</p>
            <p>
               <hi>No,</hi> (reply'd ſhe,) <hi>it is not that; What then could you deſire?</hi> (I anſwer'd) <hi>that I were not highly oblig'd to perform, though you ſhould not free me out of Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>It is,</hi> (ſaid ſhe,) <hi>that you ſhould conduct me into</hi> Spain, <hi>where, when I am Arrived, you ſhould be at liberty to go, and to do what you pleaſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I preſently did find that this would not mend my buſineſs, but there was not any thing that I would not have done, to get out of Priſon, hoping to defend my ſelf better when got at liberty; Therefore I told the <hi>Dut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheſs, That what ſhe deſir'd of me, was rather an Honour then an Acknowledg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; and that I ſhould receive a very great ſatisfaction in doing her that ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice;</hi> And having ask'd her where we ſhould go, ſhe anſwered me with
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:47240:65"/>a Tranſport of Joy; <hi>Preſently, if I pleas'd, that there was a Veſſel ready in the Harbour to tranſport us to</hi> Barce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lonia.</p>
            <p>So that I having no great prepara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions to make, we went out of my Chamber, each of us cover'd with Hooded Coats, after the manner of the Souldiers of that Country; We did paſs without any oppoſition quite through the Guards of the Caſtle, and came to the Key, where there was a <hi>Shallop</hi> that waited for us, which did carry us on Board the Veſſel, and that very Night, the Wind being favour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able, we weigh'd Anchor for <hi>Barcelo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nia:</hi> I then began to feel ſome com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Dutcheſs,</hi> who did very well Imagine that we ought to part ſo ſoon as we arrived in <hi>Spain,</hi> either for conveniency, or that ſhe did believe that I did not Love her at ſuch a rate, as to wholly give my ſelf up unto her ſervice, ſhe did make all the advantage that ſhe could, of that ſhort time
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:47240:65"/>which was ſo favourable to her de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires.</p>
            <p>I muſt confeſs, that my heart did not plead very much in her behalf: But ſo many things which ſhe had done for me, did require ſo much of gratitude and acknowledgment, that it perform'd out of duty, that which it was to have done through the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctates of Love,</p>
            <p>Of certain, had I never lov'd any other but ſhe, we had been both the more happy; for ſhe did deſerve a Gallant Perſons whole heart.</p>
            <p>I would often tell her ſo much, and give her a true account of my heart; but all that I could do did not in the leaſt abate any thing of her Affections towards me.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thereſia</hi> was Dead, and therefore ſhe having nothing but ſome few mournful Idea's to overcome, that had no Charms in them, ſhe did not diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pair to compaſs her deſign in ſome ſhort ſpace of time.</p>
            <pb n="117" facs="tcp:47240:66"/>
            <p>At laſt we Arriv'd at <hi>Barcelonia,</hi> where the <hi>Dutcheſs,</hi> no more then I, did not think fit to make our ſelves known.</p>
            <p>We both Writ from thence to our Relations about our Concerns, and ſhe had no deſire to go to <hi>Madrid,</hi> till ſhe had receiv'd an anſwer; which ſhe did ſometime after, though not very pleaſing.</p>
            <p>The Court had been already in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form'd of her flight, by an Expreſs from the <hi>Duke:</hi> And her Action had been render'd there, the moſt guilty in the World; Of truth there were ſome circumſtances in it, that could not well be excus'd, eſpecially thoſe wherein I was concern'd; ſo that her Relations being Highly Incenſed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt her, they Writ her word, that all that ſhe had to do, was to return to her Husband, and that ſhe ſhould be but very ill receiv'd at <hi>Madrid,</hi> ſhould ſhe come there; where there was no more Friends or Relations on her account, if ſhe would not follow their Councels.</p>
            <pb n="118" facs="tcp:47240:66"/>
            <p>Thoſe Letters did ſorely afflict her, and I was concern'd at them my ſelf as much as I could be.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>You ſee my Lord,</hi> (ſaid ſhe,) <hi>how that all the World does forſake me, and you are upon the point of doing the like.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Who I Madam!</hi> (I reply'd,) <hi>I hope that you know me better, to make that Judgment of me: I will not leave you, till you are no longer in a condition of having occaſion of my ſervices.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Ah! my Lord,</hi> (reply'd ſhe Sigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing,) <hi>how contented ſhould I be, not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding all my misfortunes, if I could but believe that what you do for me, did proceed from a meer effect of your Heart, that only Thought would comfort me, againſt all my Misfortunes and Afflictions.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>I have told you more then once, Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam,</hi> (I reply'd,) <hi>that I had not a Heart that was Inſenſſible, and that you had acted too much for me, not to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge.</hi>—</p>
            <pb n="119" facs="tcp:47240:67"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Will you never ſpeak to me,</hi> (an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer'd ſhe, interrupting of me,) <hi>but of acknowledgments.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>It is tenderneſs that I require from you; you know Madam,</hi> (I reply'd,) <hi>that I have of it for you, as much as I am capable to have.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Yes I know,</hi> (reply'd the <hi>Dutcheſs</hi>) <hi>that you have but very little of it for me, moſt miſerable that I am, who having abandon'd and done all things for a Man, have yet much to do, to be belov'd by him.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>She could not end thoſe words without Tears. At which I being quite Molifi'd, <hi>What is it that you de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire of me?</hi> (I cried out,) <hi>all that the moſt paſſionate Love can do, I will per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>You will do all things,</hi> (reply'd the <hi>Dutcheſs,</hi>) <hi>but Love me; and beſide that what can I deſire from you?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Do you doubt,</hi> (I reply'd,) <hi>of my Love?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Ah!</hi> (reply'd ſhe) <hi>would I could not.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="120" facs="tcp:47240:67"/>
            <p>We often had ſuch like diſcourſes, which would ſomewhat comfort her in her afflictions.</p>
            <p>At laſt, ſhe was deſirous to go to <hi>Madrid,</hi> in hopes to find a Sanctuary near her Mother, who had always Lov'd her moſt tenderly, and who had not approv'd of her Marriage with the <hi>Duke;</hi> I did offer to accompany her there, as I was oblig'd to do, and in Fifteen days we came to that City.</p>
            <p>She was receiv'd by her Mother, with that tenderneſs, which ſhe had expected.</p>
            <p>As for my part, I remain'd unknown and concern'd, in a Houſe that was not far from hers, and where ſhe dai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly did viſit me, in a Thouſand ſorts of diſguiſes, her Mother having that Complaiſance for her, that all Women have that Love their Daughters.</p>
            <p>But at laſt wearied with that ſad and ſedentary life, and it concerning my reputation alſo, as well as my li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty, that my being there ſhould not
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:47240:68"/>be known; I did reſolve to depart, for fear at laſt of being diſcover'd, as it could not fail in time to happen.</p>
            <p>I mention'd it to the <hi>Dutcheſs,</hi> and told her, <hi>That it was time for us to part.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>That word as if it had been a Thun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der-ſtroke, did not only affright her Soul, but overcame her Heart alſo; at which changing colour, <hi>Part</hi> (ſaid ſhe,) and after that a flood of Tears did hinder her from continuing.</p>
            <p>I let her know, with a ſenſible air, <hi>That ſhe ſhould have expected it; And that ſhe did know that we had agreed at firſt, that I ſhould not be above three days at</hi> Madrid, <hi>and that it was about three weeks ſince our Arrival there.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Alas, and what is three weeks,</hi> (re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply'd ſhe,) <hi>where there is Love?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Yes,</hi> (continu'd ſhe,) <hi>I did expect that if Love did once lead you to</hi> Madrid, <hi>that it would have detain'd you there during three days; But do you Love, and then you will know what three days are in Love, which cannot be confin'd to three weeks.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="122" facs="tcp:47240:68"/>
            <p>I did endeavour to defend my ſelf againſt all thoſe reaſons of Love, which ſhe alledg'd, by reaſons of Intereſt.</p>
            <p>Saying, that both our concerns did require ſome ſmall time of ſeperation, and that one ſingle unfortunate mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment were capable of running us both, that we ſhould be narrowly watched by her Husbands Friends; and that if ever it ſhould ſo unhappily fall out, that they ſhould prye into our viſits, that I might take leave of my liberty, and of her alſo; that I would be im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediately mew'd up in a Priſon, and ſhe in a Monaſtry.</p>
            <p>From thoſe reaſons, that ſhe would not allow of, I paſs'd to thoſe which concerns the affairs of the Heart, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſting to her <hi>That ſome Months of ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence, ſhould not in the leaſt diminiſh that paſſion which I had for her, and that ſhe ſhould have the ſatisfaction one day to ſee me return to</hi> Madrid, <hi>with more paſſion then ever for her, ſo ſoon as our concerns were in a better poſture.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="123" facs="tcp:47240:69"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Good Heavens!</hi> (cry'd ſhe, with Eyes full of Tears,) <hi>with what aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance can I build upon thoſe promiſes, the very impatiency that you ſhew of leaving me,</hi> (continu'd ſhe,) <hi>does contradict what you ſay,</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>You are ſtill perfidious, and your de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigns in leaving me, are but to run after ſome new ingagements, which will make you forget that which you have for me.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I did endeavour to ſettle her, and to divert her from all thoſe fears: And as it is no difficult thing for a Lover that pleaſes, to perſwade what he will; I at laſt gain'd her on my ſide, and made her reſolve to ſee me go within three days.</p>
            <p>Thoſe three days were no ſooner expir'd, but that her Tears began a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>freſh, to ask me another; ſo that e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very night I took leave of her, and every morning I was retain'd.</p>
            <p>But at laſt my Affairs groing worſe by ſuch a length of time ill employ'd, and my Enemies taking advantages from my neglects; I did ſee the ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolute
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:47240:69"/>neceſſity that there was to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part, which I was reſolv'd to do with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out giving notice to the <hi>Dutcheſs</hi> of it, but all in vain, for by three the next Morning ſhe was at my Lodgngs, where ſhe did ſtrangely ſurpriſe me; There we began our Careſſes a new, there were Tears, Sighs, Groanes, Faintings, and all the Sorrows that could accompany ſo cruel a ſepara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; but it could not divert me from the reſolution that I had taken.</p>
            <p>So that after I had been ſome hours in comforting her; I got into a Coach, which carried me half a League out of town, where my Horſes waited for me, and having paſs'd through <hi>France,</hi> I went into <hi>Flanders,</hi> where I ſtill purſue my Concernes.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
